<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine sermons vpon diuers texts of Scripture. Preached by Gervase Nid Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Nid, Gervase, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848569</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848569</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1179:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine sermons vpon diuers texts of Scripture. Preached by Gervase Nid Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Nid, Gervase, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for Walter Burre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:1"/>
            <p>CERTAINE <hi>SERMONS</hi> Vpon diuers Texts <hi>of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached by GERVASE NID Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES for WALTER BURRE</p>
            <p>1616</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN God GEORGE, by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, Lord Arch-biſhop of Canterbury, Primate of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Metropolitane, and one of his Maieſties moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Priuy Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My good Lord</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>T is not vaine oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which hath moued mee to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe Scrmons; they that know mee, know, that I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any of thoſe whom S. <hi>Baſil</hi> cals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which I haue heard your
<pb facs="tcp:13672:3"/>Grace well interprete, <hi>Selfe-putting-forth fellowes.</hi> But being to leaue your Graces ſeruice, I thought meete to depoſe theſe as a ſmall teſtimony of my thankfulneſſe. Secondly, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to commend another Treatiſe to your Graces Patronage, I reſolued to premiſe theſe: it being ſome difficulty to finde roome for things of ſmaller valew in this voluminous age, which is ſo piled vp with bookes: for who ſees not, that now the fate of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is the ſame with Preachers, whereof Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> complaines in his time:
<note place="margin">Com. in Eccleſ. <hi>9.11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nam videas in Eccleſia imperitiſſimos quoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> florere, &amp; quia nutrierunt frontis audaciam, &amp; volubilitatem linguae conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuti ſunt, prudentes ſe &amp; crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos arbitrantur, maxime ſi fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem vulgi habuerint:</hi> You may ſee how in the Church the moſt ignorant are moſt eſteemed, and becauſe they haue profited in boldneſſe of front,
<pb facs="tcp:13672:3"/>and volubility of tongue, they thinke themſelues wiſe and learned men; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if the vulgar fauour them. But I know your Grace euer hated long Salutations, therefore I haſt to take my leaue: reſting,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to bee commanded. GERVASE NID.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13672:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON. Of Murther.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 IOH. 3.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Not as <hi>Cain</hi> who was of the deuill and ſlew his brother, and wherefore ſlew hee him? becauſe his owne workes were euill and his brothers good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the will of God that deadly ſinnes ſhould not die, that they which take away the life of men, ſhould not bee able to take away life from the memory of their wicked deeds: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Diuine Hiſtory the deteſtable facts of ſinners are infamous and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſpectacles threatening and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing a farre off: To this end the pillar
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13672:5"/>of Salt was erected, and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, of the combuſtion of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and her neighbour Citties, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>they lye out as an apparant, and prominent ſpectacle:</hi> that bituminous lake doth ſtill demonſtrate the ebullition of vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall luſt. So <hi>Cain</hi> who murdered his brother in the beginning of the world, ſtill hangeth vpon a gibbet vntill the worlds end.</p>
            <p>All manner of death is mute,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.17.</note> and the graue is called <hi>Domus ſilentum:</hi> onely thoſe that are murdered talke after they are dead,
<note place="margin">Reu. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>How long Lord:</hi> and in the 11 to the Hebrewes, <hi>Abel</hi> the iuſt being dead, yet ſpeaketh: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where ſpeakes hee? marry in Scripture, ſaith <hi>Beza:</hi> whereſoeuer there is relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this murther, they bee the words of the bloud of <hi>Abel.</hi> So the words which I haue read ſuppoſe them to bee ſighes of <hi>Abel</hi> rendred from his graue: <hi>Gemitus lachrymabililis im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, auditur tumulo,</hi> as the bloud of <hi>Polydor</hi> in <hi>Virgil,</hi> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth flie or depart: ſo the bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> bids beware, eſchew: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Be not like to Cain who ſlew his brother, &amp;c.</hi> which words haue three parts: Firſt, a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13672:5"/>dehortation from being like vnto <hi>Cain,</hi> in the firſt words, <hi>Not as Cain.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a deſcription of the perſon to whom wee muſt not bee like: 1. from his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or quality, he is of the deuill: 2. from his fact, he ſlew his brother. The third part containes the cauſe that moued <hi>Cain</hi> to this horrible fact, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of a queſtion and an anſwere, the queſtion, wherefore ſlew hee him, the anſwere becauſe, &amp;c. heere be two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues; one outward, the ſight of his brothers vertues, the other inward, the beholding of his owne vices: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of which two, ſtrucke ſuch a fire of hatred within him (ſtrange mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) as would not bee extinguiſhed but by his brothers bloud.</p>
            <p>Firſt then of the dehortation, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, <hi>Not as Cain.</hi> The ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which euer ſuffered more calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation from her owne, was ſlandered by heretickes for the narration of euill deeds; whereas, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> wicked facts are alwaies expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, either where they are related, or in ſome other place of Scripture: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are ambiguous facts of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13672:6"/>Fathers, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> cuaſion to <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> and <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſimulation to his father, which as wee muſt not condemne, ſo wee muſt not imitate, not knowing whether they were ſinnes, or no ſinnes in them: but for the manifeſt crimes occurring in the Hiſtory of the Booke of God, what madneſſe to eſteeme them otherwiſe then as euill actions, in good men to bee pittyed that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwaies bee good, and to bee dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in euill men becauſe they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer but doe euill.
<note place="margin">Manacheus.</note> Yet ſuch ſpirits of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour haue not wanted; ſome condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Scriptures becauſe they record wicked deeds. Others commending wickedneſſe becauſe it is recorded in Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Tertul. praſer.</note> as the followers of <hi>Marcion</hi> and <hi>Carpecrates.</hi> And for the other kind which were doubtfull actions whether they were good or euill: if they were euill, <hi>Facta credamus, non facienda:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they were done, beleeue not that they ought to be done. And if they were good in thoſe men, it was by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary diſpenſation which is not granted vnto vs: and therefore ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, do neither excuſe the old Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcilians
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13672:6"/>from lying, nor the faithleſſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Equinocators, which ſweare with their tongues but keepe their mindes vnſworne.</p>
            <p>Now for theſe words, <hi>Not as Cain:</hi> Who would beleeue that any iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were ſo corrupt, as either to praiſe <hi>Cains</hi> fact, or to honour his perſon? but that wee reade in <hi>Tertullian, Epiphanius,</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and others, of a brood of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes called <hi>Caiani,</hi> who did honour <hi>Cain,</hi> affirming that hee was a worthy man, conceiued by ſome powerfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which therefore ſhewed it ſelfe mighty within him, that his brother was conceiued of a weaker and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our conception: The ſame Heretickes honoured <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> as men of courage and reſolution: yea, they adored <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, being perſwaded that ſome Diuine operation, and Propheticall inſtinct, did direct him, that by deliuering of his Maiſter to the Iewes, all men might bee deliuered from the deuill. Thus <hi>Adams</hi> eating of that forbidden fruite, hath put the iudgements of his poſterity out of taſte. Hence woemen long for meates that are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13672:7"/>noyſome, taking it from the firſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and all men being concelued in that corruption haue their iudgements and appetites ſo abſurd, as <hi>Dauid</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, according to the Greeke Tranfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>in ſinnes my mother longing hath conceiued mee:</hi> This <hi>Inſipience</hi> appeareth ſtrangely in ſome, that they affect and like ſuch things as bee openly repugnant vnto right reaſon, and diſtaſtefull vnto nature cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: So the <hi>Perſians</hi> admired <hi>Nero,</hi> that hatred of God and men (and as <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> reporteth) whom all others thought vnworthy of common buriall: they ſent yearely ſome with flowers and odours to adorne his ſepulcher: Thus, as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, there are men which admire none but the baſeſt wits and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureſt Authours: <hi>Neque eſt fere tam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eptus ſcriptor quin ſui ſimilem inueniet lectorem:</hi> What ſtupidity to preferre <hi>Cartright</hi> &amp; <hi>Brightman,</hi> &amp; ſuch traſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Worthies, both new and old. What is this, but in our iourny to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen to forſake the glorious Lampes which haue guided all our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, and to follow euery <hi>Ignis fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s:</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13672:7"/>euery new light: Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſenſeleſſe appetites,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.9.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe iudgements are corrupted, and out of taſte: Wherefore almighty God is not ſo much diſpleaſed with Iſrael for her ſpirituall fornications, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee was diſpleaſed, as that ſhee doated vpon ſuch beaſtly and clowniſh louers <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Aſſes and ſtallions:
<note place="margin">Ezechiel 23.30 Septuag.</note> Like <hi>Paſiphae,</hi> which doted on a Bull. The like infection is in all-thoſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings which reliſh nothing that is plaine and profitable, ancient and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, but profane nouelties: Euery wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man hath his imperfections: There is no fiſh without bones; yet ſome em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace nothing but theſe, <hi>Colligentes ſpinas librorum:</hi> Gathering thornes out of bookes, whence proceed all theſe bitter pamphlets and inuctiues: All theſe are appetites of abſurd <hi>Cainites,</hi> whom Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> did in theſe wordes preuent: And iointly all of that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: peruerſe louers, and peruerſe imitators: which thing alſo in his third Epiſtle, and verſe 11, hee general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbiddeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13672:8"/>
Beloued be not imitators of that which is euill: the Holy Ghoſt fore-ſaw that ſuch beſotted iniquities would ariſe, that the examples of wickedneſſe would bee ſo abuſed, therefore hee thought it not needleſſe to ſet this marke vpon them, <hi>Not as Cain,</hi> enuious and murtherous, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16. not as <hi>Eſau,</hi> fornicators and prophane. It is the crooked diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man to promote his ſinfull acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by ſuch examples as ſhould reſtraine him. So whereas amongſt the Grecians ſome vſed to drinke out of a dead mans ſcull, to moderate their pleaſures by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their mortality, others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it to the prouocation of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>Further, if they doe not thus peruert examples, yet how little are they moued by them: wherefore doth the world ſtill offend vpon the ſame, and no ſinne can be conſumed by puniſhment, although the monuments of precedent ages doe exclaime againſt vs, and there is no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender which hath not ſeene others pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by the ſame ſinne. O ſeeke not your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13672:8"/>death in the error of your life: looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your predeceſſors: Thou intendeſt murder, behold <hi>Caine,</hi> how he is ſtricken with the palſie of an affrighted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a quaking runnagate, reſtleſſe when he reſteth, tormented with repentleſſe horrour, and vnprofitable griefe. And is not euery homicide ſigned in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head?</p>
            <p>Now followeth the deſcription of this wicked perſon, firſt of his nature, and badneſſe of diſpoſition, he was of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. Euery worker of imquity is the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels baſtard, and the Diuell is a father, not by ſubſtantiall procreation, but by originall cauſe and ſimilitude of diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For as there is <hi>ſemen Dei,</hi> the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſeed, whereby the begotten of God are the ſonnes of God: ſo there is <hi>ſemen Diabolt,</hi> and that is concupiſcence, which conceiueth and bringeth forth vnto the Diuell: hence ſloweth that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of nature which diſcouereth the true father of the children: firſt in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, none are like vnto him, but they that paint ſaith <hi>Tertullian:</hi> but in ſpeech, in geſture, in action innumerable: in ſpeech, all ſlaunderers and detracters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he Diuels, and ſhe Diuels, <hi>Tit us</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13672:9"/>2.3. In geſture, hee that winketh with his eye, treades with his foote, ſignifieth with his fingers for to raiſe diſſention, he is a ſonne of Beliall,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.13.</note> as <hi>Salomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth: and as for action, when ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is growne to ripe age, and maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of defection, the children of Sathan doc ſo reſemble their father, that they bee often ſuppoſed fiends incarnate: ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>Elimas</hi> the Magician ſon of the Diuell,
<note place="margin">Acts 13.10.</note> becauſe he was repleniſhed with all deceit.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Caine</hi> is not onely begotten, but firſt begotten of this euill one, the firſt branch of ſinne, the firſt propagated e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Marke how ſoone ill weeds ſhoote vp: the mother is corrupted of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and the firſt ſhe beares is a ſerpent, who no ſooner growne able, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his father: the father the firſt murtherer of ſoules, the ſonne the firſt murtherer of bodies: the father procures the firſt curſe vpon the earth, the ſonne procures the ſecond: the father firſt brought in death, the ſonne vntimely death. And ſure, if you obſcrue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of Satan, (let no diſcreet man bee offended) you ſhall finde that it much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13672:9"/>tanne vpon the elder brothers. Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that Satan may bee called an elder brother, being the chiefe of the wayes of God,
<note place="margin">Iob. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt eldeſt brother in the old world, then cutſed <hi>Cham</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eldeſt of the new world, and wild <hi>Iſmael</hi> the eldeſt to the father of the faithfull, and prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> which ſold his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, the father of all vnthrifty heires, which ſell their honour for their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Laſtly, <hi>Ruben,</hi> which deſiled his fathers bed. But we reade in the Goſpel, that the elder liued ſoberly at home: the running Prodigall was a yonger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This I obſerue, firſt to note the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of Satan, becauſe the firſt borne is Gods, therefore he endeuoureth his vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt for that: ſecondly, how the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie ſuffers him to carry it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, perhaps to ſignifie that theſe firſt fruits of nature are not in ſuch high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt with God: there is a new creature, a ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> which he eſteemeth, which therefore he cauſeth to ſpring often out of yonger &amp; inſcrior Nature, becauſe the excellencies of nature were ſo vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him. Againe, to abate the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of prime Nature, wherewith the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13672:10"/>moſt ſpirituall ſonnes of God haue been taken. <hi>O that Iſmael might liue in thy ſight,</hi> ſaith <hi>Abraham.</hi> And <hi>Iſaac</hi> would gladly haue bleſſed <hi>Eſau,</hi> but God would not. So <hi>Ioſeph</hi> would gladly put the right hand of his father vpon <hi>Manaſſeth:</hi> and in <hi>Iacob</hi> I heare the voyce of Nature Iamenting, <hi>Ruben my eldeſt ſonne, my might and the beginning of my ſtrength, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of dignitie, and the excellency of power: thou waſt light as water, thou canſt not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and thy dignitie is gone.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſeeing in this corrupt maſſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, the firſt generation that was formed was euill, it argues that no man is good which is not firſt regenerated out of euill. <hi>Nemo bonus qui non ex mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bonus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt the ſpirit of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> Who knowes not the vanitie of the Manichies, and the dotage of <hi>Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieus,</hi> who out of this and other places made ſinne ſubſtantiall, and the Diuell a creator of ſinfull men: which follies to name is to confute them.</p>
            <p>Neither am I perſwaded, that euill ſpirits haue any part in the generation of the moſt vngratious natures, although the worthieſt Chriſtian wits did hold,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13672:10"/>that they had knowledge of the faire daughters of men, and thence to haue proceeded the race of Giants, as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous for their vices and conditions, as vaſt and enormious in their bodies, that this infectious and deteſtable ſeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſperſed through the whole earth, doth now and then ſpring vp and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch abhominable monſters as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liogabalus</hi> and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and other carnall fiendes. The prodigious lewdneſſe of ſome violent, and in corrigible natures hath cauſed this opinion more probable then true: howſocuer, it is ſure the Diuel hath a lineage vpon earth, and <hi>Cain</hi> is the moſt ancient of that kindred.</p>
            <p>In this paire of brothers were the two houſes firſt diuided, and as they begun with fighting, ſo they haue continued vntill now. Hence multiplied the two Cities, <hi>Cinitas Dei, &amp; Terrena ciuitas.</hi> whoſe beginnings, proceedings, and wonderful variety of fortunes, how lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly hath S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> followed in thoſe ſweet bookes which begin <hi>Glorioſiſſimam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuitatem Dei.</hi> Where he teacheth how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man belongs to one of thoſe Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being deſcended either of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13672:11"/>of <hi>Cain,</hi> or of the bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> which <hi>Cain</hi> ſpilt. There are but two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: if thou beeſt of <hi>Abels</hi> bloud, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what houſe thou commeſt of, by thy innocency, &amp; patience of the Saints: If thou art of <hi>Caines</hi> kindred, then deny not thy name, bee content to bee num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongſt thine owne. And thus much of the nature of <hi>Cain.</hi> Of the ſtocke and diſcent: he is <hi>ex maligno</hi> of the Diuel, of the malignant faction: to conclude, a veſſell of diſhonour, made of the corrupt maſſe: for if he had not beene of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, he ſhould not haue beene euill: <hi>hac enim,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 106</note> maſſa, ſi ita eſſet media: vt quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum nihil bont ita nec mali aliquid mereretur non fruſtra videretur iniquitas vt ex ea fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vaſa in contumeliam.</hi> This maſſeiſ it were of indifferent quality neither good nor euill, there might be cauſe to thinke it iniuſtice in God to make out of it any veſſels of diſhonour.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch as the tree is, ſuch is the fruit. Who <hi>was of the Dinell,</hi> there is the tree: <hi>who ſlew his brother,</hi> there is the fruit: bitter and deadly fruit, eſpecially in the manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word ſignifies to cut in peeces like a ſacrifice, becauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13672:11"/>he had ſacrificed ſo well. <hi>Cain</hi> would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice him. So <hi>Pilat</hi> mixed the <hi>Galileans</hi> bloud with their ſacrifice. And at the time of Immolation of the Paſſouer, the Iewes ſacrificed the innocent lambe of God: thus the innocent when they are murdered, they are offered to God in contempt of God, and his worſhip, that they may ſeeme to periſh by him in whom they truſted. Another circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is of the time how ſoone <hi>Cain</hi> ſhed bloud, and the Diuell ſlaieth in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: in the morning of youth, and in the morning of the world. By him death entered, and how hee longeth to ſee it worke? and that in the firſt bloſſome of vertue. It is his cunning to ſtop the firſt ſtep to goodneſſe, therefore haue care of the beginning of thy wayes of thy youth and good endeuours, for there the Diuell is moſt inſtant; he knowes well, that in euery beginning is contained more then a beginning. As ſoone as the Temple began to be re-edified, he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mainly, hee ſtirred euery ſtone, that no ſtone might bee ſtirred. And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately when the Sauiour of our ſoules beganne the office of Chriſt, the Diuell
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13672:12"/>tempted him in the deſart: ſo in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity of the creation, he ſlew the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of Nature, and in the entrance of generation, the firſt innocencie of grace. So he perſecuted the tender infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of our Lord, and he made the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church to ſwim with bloud. Hee knew that if the world were ſtained when it was a new veſſell, that colour would continue vnto the end. So <hi>Rome</hi> an Epitome of the world, in token that it ſhould be died with the bloud of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, the foundations of her walles were dipt in brothers bloud. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> both elder brothers, both furious &amp; potent: <hi>Cain</hi> in his name, which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth poſſeſſion, ſhewed that he had elenen parts againſt one: ſo <hi>Achab</hi> killed <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> and tooke poſſeſſion, and euer the greater part ouercommeth the better: <hi>Abel</hi> could not kill <hi>Cain</hi> if he would; but where might and malice, wealth and wrath are ioyned, there breake forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuties and oppreſſions. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wealth brings forth wrong.</hi> Wherfore God ſet a marke vpon <hi>Cain,</hi> that men might beware of him. As the Romans vſed to bind ſome hay to the hornes of a madde
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13672:12"/>Bull, to ſignifie (ſaith <hi>Plutarke</hi>) that too much ſodder made him mad; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they applyed this prouerbe: <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num habet in cornu:</hi> beware of him that is iniurious and rich. Now as <hi>Cain</hi> was a patterne of all oppreſſours, hauing power, and doing wrong: ſo <hi>Abel</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying vanity, in the beginning, was a type not onely of death, but of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of life; for euery man liuing is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vanity: How many haue their ſunne-ſetting in the morning, and they which haue the longeſt day, liue but a day, ſo ſoone doe wee appeare, and vaniſh. Vanity in apparell, walking in a vaine ſhadow, talking vainely, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietting our ſelues in vaine, vaine hopes, and vaine deſires. <hi>In the daies of my vanity</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) I ſaw this and that vanity, and whatſoeuer I beheld was vanity of vanities. Another thing was allegorized in this Hiſtory, namely, how our Sauiour Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> was murthered by the Elders of the Iewes, and his Bloud ſhed, though ſpeaking better things then that of <hi>Abel.</hi> without the gates, as <hi>Abels</hi> in the fields: for which horrible ſinne of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13672:13"/>the Iewes ſhall bee errant va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds vnto the worlds end, ſigned by God, that although all men hate and eſchew them, yet none ſhall kill them. <hi>Deſtroy them not O God</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>leaſt my people forget it, but ſcatter and deſpearſe them:</hi> So they are aliens in the whole earth, a common prouerbe, a common prey, not borne but by leaue, nor breathing but by good will. And ſurely it is ſeldome ſeene, but ſhame and beggery is the end of thoſe which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the innocent, either by the mouth of the ſword, or by the ſword of the mouth: and they which kill mens ſoules by hereſy and ſeluſme, and they which ſlay by hatred, and they which rauen and oppreſſe. As the great fiſh eates the leſſe, and the greater cates the great, and the greateſt the greater; ſo greedy <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> deuoure and are deooured, but at laſt the biggeſt (ſaith S. <hi>Baſil</hi>) comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the net, and the deuill rips the prey out of his bowels, thou appeares the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiableneſſe of theſe ſwallow-goods that haue more riches then they can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, when the whole eſtate of ſuch and ſuch a man, ſhall bee found in their bags
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13672:13"/>indigeſted. The laſt degree of <hi>Cain</hi> his exceeding wickedneſſe, that hee killed his brother, his naturall brother, and his onely brother; and which aggrauates his villany, in whom were all the kinds and degrees of brother-hood vndiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For then there were not brothers, ſome by the father, ſome by the mother, brothers by friendſhip not by bloud, brothers by affinity not by conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, brothers, that is, the ſame Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men not ſtrangers, brothers of the ſame Religion and not diuers, but all theſe ſtrings of loue and affection they were vnited in one. Neither did he it for want of lands and territories: for was he not heire of the whole earth? but Ambition and Couetouſneſſe are impatient of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort and fellowſhip, be they neuer ſo much dilated. Further, by this murther <hi>Caine</hi> is guilty of the bloud of Chriſt, and all the bleſſed Progeny, which ſhould haue beene deriued from him. Nay yet further, he hath ſlaine all poſterities that followed, all generations may call him curſed: For if God had deſtroyed him, and giuen <hi>Eue</hi> no more children, as iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he might haue done, the propogation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13672:14"/>of man-kind had beene cut off, and this faire world ſhut vp, as ſoone as it was made, like goodly new houſes which haue no inhabitants.</p>
            <p>But the loue of brothers will not ſuffer me to paſſe it thus, which the more ſacred it is, with the greater ſinne was it violated by this vnnaturall. Why did he not conſider that hauing a brother his ſtrength was doubled? For what are brothers but two in one, two in labour but one in enioying, two againſt all others, one betwixt themſelues? What aduantage is it to bee in two places at once, to watch when he ſleepeth, to haue his health when hee is ſick, and all this not by a deputy, but by himſelfe? for this vnion is in ſome ſence naturall, not onely of affection. Two hands, two feet, two eyes, two cares, in one body, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble brothers, which are two bodies in one. Wherefore fraternall loue being a patterne of all loue, when wee would haue any to loue entirely wee ſtile them by the name of brethren. As brethren enuy not one another: for the loue of husband and wife though it bee great, yet it is not naturall but grafted, the loue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13672:14"/>of parents and children greater, but not reciprocall, for loue deſcendeth not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth, but the loue of brothers is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and collaterall, neither ouer-awed with reuerence, nor by ſatiety inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>How full of ſweetneſſe is it, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, (ſaith <hi>Valerius</hi>) that we liued in the ſame lodging before that we were borne, and paſt the time of our infancy in the ſame cradle, ſmiled vpon the ſame parents, preſerued by the ſame prayers and vowes, drawing equall honour from the ſame Anceſtors? hauing had the ſame parents, the ſame wombe, the ſame bloud, the ſame beginning, the ſame education, the ſame nobility, the ſame eſtate, the ſame diſcipline, why ſhould they not will and nill the ſame, bee of the ſame minde and affections? But this is the miſchiefe of ſinne and of the deuill, that the ſweeteſt loue turneth into the ſharpeſt hatred, brothers being incenſed are vnquenchable; as much water will not quench their loue, ſo not the Ocean their hatred. Becauſe euery iniury is more grieuous proceeding from a friend, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; what will <hi>Brutus</hi> ſtab
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13672:15"/>
               <hi>Caeſar?</hi> that ſtrikes him to the heart. And our Sauiour to his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Iohn 6.</note> 
               <hi>will you alſo forſake mee?</hi> you? But this woefull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of brethren is not vſually kindled but by extraordinary wrong. What was it that enſlamed <hi>Cain,</hi> wherefore ſlew he him?</p>
            <p>This interrogation is to ſtirre vs to attention, and makes way for an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reaſon following:
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.22.</note> for no man will demand of himſelfe vnleſſe his anſwere be plaine and ready. Then the reaſon is becauſe his owne workes were euill, and his brothers good. Becauſe his owne workes were euill, therefore will he make them worſe? and becauſe his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers workes were good, did that onely offend him that his brother did not offend? if he liked his owne euill workes better, why was he not content with them? and if he loued his brothers good workes, why did he not make his owne like them? So wickedneſſe is loathſome to the wicked, yet he will retaine it, and thought he chuſe to bee euill, yet he would not bee ſo accounted. But what were his euill workes? No man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſinfull all at once, vice groweth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13672:15"/>vpon men by degrees, therefore before this oblation it is probable that he was diſobedient to his parents, proud, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous, preferring the world, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſimplicity of innocency, and the infirmity of vertue, and comming thus affected how could his offering pleaſe God? how could the fruites of the earth be acceptable, when the fruites of good workes were wanting? an honeſt man will not take a gift from a knaue, much leſſe will God admit of ſuch giftleſſe giftes. Thought he by thoſe giftes to bribe the Almighty, and procure connei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance to his ſinnes? ſo it was: and ſo it is the daily practiſe of ſecular manners, to ſerue God onely to make vſe of him: for as religious men (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>) doe vſe the world that they may enioy GOD; ſo the vngodly do vſe GOD that they may more freely enioy the world, which indeed is to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a friend of the righteous GOD, that they may more plenteouſly enioy the vnrighteous Mammon. <hi>Abel</hi> was not thus conditioned, but offered vnto God himſelfe alſo by mortification, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed in the faith of that alone Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13672:16"/>to come with liuing ſacrifice God accepted, neglecting the inanimate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Cain, Viua accipien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> terrenare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſans,</hi> ſaith <hi>Prudentius:</hi> the ſight of theſe vertues made <hi>Cain</hi> to deiect his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and enuy followed, and murther the brood of enuy. So the brethren of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being moued with enuy, ſold him into Egypt, and there can bee nothing excellent, but the eye of enuy eſpyes it. An euill eye (ſaith our Sauiour) therfore euill becauſe anothers is good, a ſore eye which cannot endure to looke vpon a quality that is bright and amiable in his brother. This inſatiable vice being that which firſt moued the Diuell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our nature intire, and firſt moued <hi>Cain</hi> againſt <hi>Abel,</hi> it is one alſo of the firſt vices which appeareth in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Vidi puerum amaro vultu in tuentem collactaneum ſuum.</hi> I haue ſeene an infant (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) looke bitterly vpon his fellow-ſuckling,
<note place="margin">Confeſſ.</note> and it is one of the laſt ſinnes. Hence is bewitching com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in old women, which antiquitie did beleeue to be effected by the poyſon of an enuious eye, as appeareth by the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>faſcinus</hi> that is, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13672:16"/>with the eye: this made them ſo fearefull of any ſingular or admirable nature, leaſt it ſhould bee blaſted with enuy, and periſh, eſpecially if it were a maturitie before his ſeaſon, <hi>praecox fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> a haſty fruit, wit or valour aboue his yeares. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ſaith <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander,</hi> therfore when any one praiſed it, they were wont to ſay, <hi>prefiſcini,</hi> God bleſſe it; leaſt perhaps ſelfe-loue might breed within it, or rather, becauſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy did pretend flattery; I omit ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but ſure it is, whether the world be not worthy of things worthy, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God permits the diuel ſtill to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his inueterate enuy, or whether the ſubſtance of theſe beauties is not dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, howſoeuer it is, things wonderfully amiable, haue no long continuance. Whilſt vertue is in health, malice hates it, and loue neglects it; and if it periſh not quickly of it ſelfe, enuy murders it: enuy will conſume it ſelfe vntill it bee conſumed. Which coniunction of enuy and murther, the Greekes expreſſed in the ſimilitude of their names: there is but one letter betweene enuy &amp; death;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that is a deadly and diſmall letter.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13672:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13672:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13672:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13672:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13672:19"/>So the Apoſtle ioynes them together:
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.19</note> 
               <hi>Full of enuy and murther.</hi> And <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. <hi>The workes of the fleſh are enuies and murthers.</hi> Wherefore if thou wilt preuent the one, ſuppreſſe the other. Thou beholdeſt in another that good which is not in thy ſelfe: either it is thine owne fault, or in recompence thou haſt that which hee wanteth. Or why doeſt thou maligne him when God gaue it him? or may not God diſpoſe of his owne? or is there not another world to giue euery man ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Further, alaſſe what is there in this world worthy of enuy? is not euery good thing haunted with his ſpirit? are not the vertues of the beſt poore inough, but wee muſt paire them by detraction? if thou wilt needs enuy, enuy within thy ſelf, to ſee the worſe part get the better, to ſee the proſperitie &amp; inſolencie of the fleſh aboue the ſpirit. Woe to them (ſaith Saint <hi>Iude</hi>) which <hi>walke in the way of Cain:</hi> for they contemne the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of Grace, for they admire things tranſitorie, and there is no loue in them. From which ſinnes the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirit of loue preſerue vs, which combineth the Father and the Sonne,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13672:19"/>vnto whom one GOD bee all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, praiſe, and confeſſion for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13672:20"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON. Of Humane Miſerie.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOB. 3.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore is the light giuen to him that is in miſery, and life to them which are bitter in ſpirit?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HINGS Tragicall which in themſelues are fearefull and vnpleaſant, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented or remembred with delight. But beſides that the ſuffsrings of the Saints recorded in Scripture, doe affoord vnto a Chriſtian further inſtruction, namely with the Greeke Church to pray to haue his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13672:20"/>in this life, and to ſay with S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten; Domine hic ſeca, hic vre, vt in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num parcas.</hi> Lord here lance mee, and here laſh me, that thou maiſt ſpare mee for euer. A famous patterne of theſe paſſions was happy <hi>Iob,</hi> and amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his tragicall exclamations is this miſerable and dolefull complaint pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the aboundance of his griefe. In which text conſider two things, Firſt the griefe and paſſion of <hi>Iobs</hi> minde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by an interrogation, <hi>quare, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> Secondly, the cauſe and matter of his griefe in the words following, which is the miſery of mankind, and that hee diuides into two kinds, the troubleſome things which we do, out of theſe words, <hi>light</hi> and <hi>labour:</hi> and the miſerable things that we ſuffer in the words following, <hi>and life to them that are bitter in ſpirit.</hi> For hee thinketh that light doth aggrauate our labours, and life augment our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
            <p>This interrogation <hi>wherefore</hi> is not a word of indignation or murmure againſt God, but of ſorrow and complaint. For ſighes and groanes, and miſerable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, they are the irruptions of a heart
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13672:21"/>burdened with griefe, which if it ſhould not finde paſſage that way, would bee combuſt, or cleaue aſunder. And they are cauſed oftentimes from extreame heate and affection of loue, when the minde being ſtricken with ſome vnexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, vttereth tearmes which ſeeme to be of hatred and diſgrace, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding doe indeed proceed one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the affection of loue troubled and diſtracted. Such affectionate ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the Pſalmes, the Canticles, and the booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> they be full of; where the Saints of God are expreſſed, varying themſelues into all ſhapes of affections. Into feare, into hope, into chiding, into weeping, into ſudden ſilence, into ſhew of deſpaire, into forſaking, and ſuddenly into earneſt intreating. Hence we learne two things: The firſt, that the violence of affection and griefe, it may be pleaſing vnto God ſometimes, and compatible with the gouernement of reaſon and of grace. There is in vs naturally in ſome more, in ſome leſſe, a ſoftneſſe and flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of nature, which takes impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of griefe: it is created of God, and the operations of it are not in vaine:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13672:21"/>When God is angry hee will haue vs grieue: when hee chides, or when hee ſcourges, hee will haue vs weepe and powre out our ſoules into deprecations and complaints. Yea then our loue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to him, when wee melt like waxe before the heate of his anger, when we ſeeke him, and ſorrow that wee cannot find him, and when wee feele the diſcontinuance of his fauour. This bleeding of the heart of man, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome both to God and to vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine: Poſſumne audire abs te Domine, Cur fletus dulcis ſit miſeris? an hoe tibi dulce eſt quod ſperamus ex audire te?</hi> Neither is the extremity of any paſſion to be blamed, but the perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diſobedience to reaſon? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee read in Scripture of the boly men of God when they were afflicted with any occaſion of griefe, that their ſorrow is expreſſed in termes of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt lamentation. They rend their hearts and their garments, they afflict their ſoules with faſting, they put on ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes, becauſe as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ieiunus venter &amp; hahitus lugubris Ambitioſius dominum deprecantur.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13672:22"/>their words are dolefull aboue all the Tragicall exclamations that Art can find. How exceeding great was the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> for the good King <hi>Ioſias?</hi> that it came to bee a Prouerbe, <hi>as the mourning of Hadadrimon in the valley of Megiddon.</hi> Wherefore there being a meane and meaſure in mourning, two extremities are to be auoided: the firſt is dulneſſe and ſenceleſſenes of heart, a pretended calmeneſſe, but indeed a ſtoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and vnnaturall careleſſeneſſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the loue of caſe and want of compaſſion and affection, either in our owne troubles, or the troubles of others. Theſe men will neither weepe, nor exclaime, nor giue any ſignes of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent paſſions, as if this were fortitude and patience, which is rather ſtupidity and want of charity. What father will like his ſonne if vpon his diſpleaſure he ſhew himſelfe nothing daunted, nor moued in his countenance, nor ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the heart, to looke pale, or to humble his voyce, or to weepe, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect his eyes? Will a father call this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, or ſtubborneſſe, in his ſonne? Such are they, who when their heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13672:22"/>Father afflicts them make haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to ſtop their paſſions, that neither teares, nor groanes, nor complaints, may finde any paſſage, through too much ſelfe-loue, or indolence, haſting to heale their hearts before they are wounded, and to comfort their conſciences before they be afflicted. Heerevpon they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all deep ſorrow and lamentation as ſoft and effeminate, or want of faith and patience, all funerall rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as Heatheniſh and Vnchriſtian, all ſolemne afflicting of the ſoule, himnes, ſupplications, faſting, and almes deeds; which notwithſtanding hath beene practiſed of holieſt men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in all ages. In the eighth of the <hi>Actes,</hi> the ſecond verſe, deuote men beare out the body of the bleſſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and made great lamentation. The word ſignifies extremity of griefe with beating and knocking of the breaſt. With what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſorrow did Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> mourne for the death of his mother? <hi>Et libuit flere in conſpectu tuo de Illa &amp; pro illa, de me &amp; pro me &amp; dimiſi, lachrimas vt efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint quantum vellent.</hi> Laſtly, which is the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13672:23"/>greateſt commendations of this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſoftneſſe of nature, wee reade that our Sauiour Chriſt was deeply mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and did weep at the departure of his friend, wherevpon the Iewes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued how greatly hee loued him. God hath created in our hearts, <hi>Dulce nomen:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this ſweete name of naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Which is as a ſparke of that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall loue wherewith the indiuided Trinity is enſlamed. Which is ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and actiue, that being moued it doth preſently heat and diſſolue the heart into paſſion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond extreme to be auoided is, immoderation of griefe, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from impatience and vnbeleefe. For when men beleeue not that God is the God of the dead, as well as of the liuing, and of the ſicke as of the whole; that all things worke vnto the good of the godly: then loue ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, and their hope, they ſorrow like them which haue no hope. And how can they haue any hope, when they want the Comforter, who is ſo called, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtiue,</hi> that they which ſuffer loſſe of things temporall might
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13672:23"/>bee comforted with hope of things eternall. Therefore when any croſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fals them, through immoderate loue of theſe tranſitory things, they are infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deiected, full of bitter thoughts, of curſing and howling, Deſperate mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, not capable of conſolation; accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of God, reuolters from Religion. One example for all, take the King of Iſraell in that miſerable ſiege and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of Samaria, how he railes; firſt, againſt the Prophet of God; ſecondly, againſt God himſelfe, for that is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, and theſe are his blaſphemous words: <hi>Behold what euill commeth from the Lord! why ſhould I wait longer vpon the Lord? Ecce tantum malia Domino, quid amplius expectabo à Domino?</hi> A true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of impatience and inſidelity. Likewiſe the Gentiles when the hand of God was vpon them, they vſed to breake out into exclamations and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations againſt God; as in that: <hi>Atque Deos, atque aſtra vocat crudelia mater.</hi> As <hi>Quiutilian: quis mihi alius vſus vocis qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt incuſem Deos?</hi> And, <hi>Iure per mala mea per infelicem conſcientiam,</hi> Hence riſe their funerall pompes, and ſuperſtitious exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13672:24"/>for the dead: Sacrificing of men and women, in honour of the defunct; ertificiall howling and cutting of their fleſh, ambitious Sepulchers, and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue feaſts of many daies continuance: In which kind euery Nation had ſome peculiar vanity and ſuperſtition aboue the reſt. Laſtly, in all their troubles and calamities they captiuate their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings to their affections, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without reſtraint, raging againſt God and his creatures. But <hi>Iobs</hi> lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was not of this kinde; neither are his words otherwaies to bee interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then as ſignes of extraordinary griefe eaſing his oppreſſed heart, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not without ſome perturbation. Hitherto of the griefe and paſſion of <hi>Iobs</hi> minde, expreſſed by this interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Quare,</hi> wherefore? Which is a word of ſorrow not of indignation.</p>
            <p>Now to the matter and cauſe of his griefe: namely, that ſuch benefites of God as light and life, ſhould bee ſo blotted with miſeries and vexation of ſpirit. Although according to the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all interpretation, theſe words haue one and the ſame ſence; light and life, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13672:24"/>labour and bitterneſſe of ſoule; yet their proper acception, and ſignification, will affoord vs this difference of diſcourſe. All the miſery of man is either labour, or bitterneſſe of ſoule: By labour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all that wee do with difficulty and impediment, whether they be acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and operations, of the mind or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. By bitterneſſe of ſoule is ment all that wee ſuffer in our ſoules, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately or from the body, or any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affliction. Theſe two diuers kinds of miſery do planely and diſtinctly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in that ſentence of woe which God pronounceth againſt <hi>Adam, In do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore comedes,</hi> heere is the miſery of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: <hi>In ſudore comedes,</hi> there is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of working. In like manner the good things which we enioy, they bee either ſuch as guide and eaſe our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which <hi>Iob</hi> comprehends vnder the name of light: or thoſe which ſuſtaine and benefite our paſſions, which are contained in the word Life. For the firſt, Light is of three ſorts; ſenſible, intellectuall, and ſpirituall. Senſible light is either artificiall, or naturall: Concerning naturall light, as of it ſelfe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13672:25"/>nothing is more ſweet and cheerefull, ſo to the ſpirit which is in wearineſſe and toyle, nothing is more tedious. In the 10 of <hi>Eccle.</hi> the 7 verſe: <hi>Lighe is ſweete.</hi> And in the Creation, light is the firſt creature that is made, and firſt hallowed. Hence is it adorned with ſo many Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thits in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Therefore as poore labourers by ſinging do ſweeten their paines; for which cauſe S. <hi>Baſil</hi> cals their ſinging <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſauce of their toyle: So the light of the Sunne doth lighten their labour, and makes them more cheerefull in their worke. Yet how much pleaſanter is light to them that are at liberty and reſt? which haue leaſure to contemplate the beauty of the heauens, or to diſcourſe of the benefites of light. But if they bee bound to ſome grieuous taxe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant labour, as the Iſraelites, then light is but an eye-ſore. Whilſt they ſee their owne vexation, and how much worke they haue to doe: whilſt they ſee others ſporting and themſelues toyling. Laſtly, whilſt they ſee their miſery to bee expoſed to the ſight of all. They ſee youth dancing, and age wooing; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13672:25"/>walking to theaters to ſee and to be ſeene. Laſtly, they ſee the day diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brute beauty and cheerofulneſſe to all creatures but vnto themſelues: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to birdes, vnto buildings, to the clouds, to the aire, to the earth, to the waters. And therefore vnto them which in time of old tyranny, were condemned <hi>ad lapicidiuas,</hi> yet this was ſome comfort, that they neither ſo much ſaw their own miſerie, nor the happineſſe of others. The Sunne in the creation was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſignes and ſeaſons, to rule the day, and to ſhine vpon the earth: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne had brought in labour, the ſun became a taske-maiſter to call men forth vnto their worke, as it is in the 104 Pſalme. <hi>The ſunne riſeth, and man go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth vnto his labour vntill the euening.</hi> Likewiſeſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the King, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of toyle and labour, hee vſually ſtiles it, <hi>Labour vnder the ſun. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fito hath a man of all his labour wherein hee labours vnder the ſinne?</hi> So that as the eye of the maiſter vrgeth the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants worke: ſo the eye of heauen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts labour, and vpbraids reſt vnto miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and mortall men. And yet when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13672:26"/>the ſunne is downe, ſtill light continues labour by artificiall lampes and candles, holding them to their taske. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the name of <hi>light</hi> this labour is called <hi>Lucubration.</hi> Therefore <hi>Iob</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the affliction of mankinde, doth fitly vſe this ſpeech, <hi>Wherefore is light gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them that labour?</hi> the ſweete ſight whereof they cannot enioy. Which haue no leaſure to feed their eyes with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant colours, or with ſights and theaters? Wherefore doe they ſee light? light the meaſure of paines, the renewer of weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the enemy of reſt, the opener of the eyes which want ſleepe. Wherefore is light giuen to augment labour, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the poore ſeruants in the night? The painfull houſewiſe riſes in the night, and holds her maides to their taske. <hi>Prou.</hi> 31. <hi>Noctem addens operi, famulaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad lumina longo exercet penſo, caſtum vt ſeruare cubile coniugis &amp; poſſit paruos educere natos.</hi> So e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Carpenter and Workemaiſter that labours day and night, and watches to finiſh a worke, <hi>operi perficiendo inuigilat.</hi> The Smith alſo by the Anuill, early and late, are not his eyes put out with too much light? whiles the vapour of the fire
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13672:26"/>waſtes his fleſh, and the noyſe of the hammer is euer beating in his earer, <hi>&amp; ad poliendum opus aduigilat,</hi> and he watcheth to poliſh his worke. To conclude then, ſeeing as light was firſt ordained for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleaſure, and to direct and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate our actions; So now ſince wee were condemned to labour and trauell, it is become tedious and cruell; let vs with <hi>Iob</hi> bewaile our finnes, which haue ſo altered our condition, and ſigh to be deliuered from the houſe of bondage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that libertie where the wearied be at reſt, where the ſeruant is free from his maiſter, and the voyce of the oppreſſour is not heard.</p>
            <p>Now beſides this ſenſible light, there is alſo the light of knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which in ſtead of ioy and delight, how it addes affliction vnto thoſe that labour, doth more eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. For as it is <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. <hi>vlt. in multa ſapientia multa indignatio, &amp; qui addit ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam, addit laborem.</hi> The eye of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is ſo owliſh, that the light of knowledge doth offend it. So that moſt men do either decline wiſedome &amp; experience, or elſe complaint of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13672:27"/>wherewith it is accompanied. It is true which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 2. That wiſedome excelles folly as much as light excelles darkneſſe: and that the eyes of a a wiſe man are in his head, but the foole walkes in darkneſſe. Yet when the light that is within vs is darkneſſe, ſaith our Sauiour, how greatis that darkeneſſe? For which cauſe wee may complaine with <hi>Iob,</hi> Wherefore is knowledge giuen to them that labour? Wherby they know this one thing, that they know nothing whereby they know God, but better what he is not then what he is. Whereby they know themſelues to be moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrable and wretched. Wherefore is knowledge giuen to thoſe that labour? whereby their labour is more increaſed by knowledge, then their knowledge by labour. Whereby they know what it is to labour. For as children and fooles are moſt indefatigable in paines, becauſe they do not prize nor eſteeme labour: ſo wiſe men, the more wiſedome they haue, the more ſenſible they are of pains, and the cogitation and weighing of their labour, makes it appeare more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and more weightie vnto them.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13672:27"/>
               <hi>Pueris continuus luſus, &amp; totius dici diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus non nocet, quia pondus illis abeſt, nec ſe ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi grauant.</hi> Children (ſaith <hi>Quintilian</hi>) are not weary, becauſe they haue not weight of vnderſtanding: but in men conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and iudgement makes their mindes more ponderous, and ſo labour becomes more difficult and burdenſome vnto them. Laſtly, this modell of knowledge which this world affords vs, is ſo ſmall, that as the Oratour ſayes of the poore pittance of a paiſoner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it neither can ſtrenthen the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor will ſuffer it to die. So this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge neither can make a man happy, nor will ſuffer ſome men to ſeeke for that knowledge which would make them happy. But this is true of intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall light, it is not ſo of ſpirituall. Yet ſurely euen this light alſo hath his ſpots of darkeneſſe. For the beames of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces which are extraordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by the holy Ghoſt, being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, illuminations, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſanctifications they are mixed with the imperfections and frailties of theſe corrupt ſoules and bodies of ours. We here ſee in part, and we know in part; and the beautie of our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13672:28"/>puritie conſiſteth more in the loue of God, then in the louelineſſe of man.</p>
            <p>Now followes the laſt part of <hi>Iobs</hi> complaint. <hi>And life to them that are bitter of ſoule.</hi> Where he laments two things: The miſery of life, and the life of miſerie. Bitterneſſe of ſoule, there is the miſerie of life. And <hi>life to them that are bitter in ſoule,</hi> that is the life of miſerie.</p>
            <p>When the childe is borne into the world, he weepes, propheſying (ſaith S. <hi>Auſten</hi>) of his miſerie to come. His cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle is his graue: hee ſuckes errour with his milke: and when his vnderſtanding firſt appeares, the weedes of bad affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſpring vp with it. Before hee knowes what vice is, hee becomes vicious. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how many cruelties do they ſuffer? whilſt ſome are ſnatcht from their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers breaſts, and either expoſed with <hi>Moſes,</hi> or daſht againſt the ſtones as the children of Babylon. Whilſt ſome are the death of thoſe that beare them, and looſe their mothers before they can ſmile vpon them. Whilſt ſome doe but once by breath take in the aire, and then breathe out their ſoules into the aire. Whom God onely ſhewes vnto the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13672:28"/>world, and takes them away as ſoone as he hath giuen them. And if they liue till youth, what ſaith the wiſe man of youth? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Youth is vanitie it ſelfe. ruled by fancie and affection, adoring pleaſure, and treaſuring vp matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for age, full of hopes and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnlity, ouer-growne with vice: by waſte and prodigalitie making warre againſt himſelfe, as diſobedient to reaſon, as to his parents. Laſtly, what is youth, but the boyling of outragious, bloud, which when it is decocted, and ſomthing more moderate by age, although it bee leſſe boaſting, yet is it more pernicious and hurtfull. For moſt men when they grow to experience and yeares, they ſtriue to put off ſimplicitie, and to put on craft. And then they haue well profited, when they can deceiue, and not bee deceiued. Their knowledge is now to vnlearne that they learned before. Their bodies how much the ſtronger, ſo much the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerenduring of ſickneſſe, of conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of death. Vaine-glorious, cruell, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, riſing by the ruines of others. Laſtly, what is man-age, but the Giant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne, and the power of miſerie?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13672:29"/>But when theſe ages of childe-hood, youth, and man-hood are worne into old age, then you haue the recapitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of humane miſerie: the infirmitie of childe-age, the incorrigibilitie of Boy-age, the ſubtiltie of Man-age: and all theſe greater here then in the former Ages. Here the prodigalitie of youth is dried vp into auarice: pride, and luſt bee ſinnes here out of faſhion, but not out of vſe, vndecent and vnbeſeeming vices. Here wiſedome doateth, and of power to ſinne is left a will to ſinne, the greater torment. Laſtly, what is old age, but the ſtore-houſe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and obliuion, the ragges of life, the aſhes of a luſtfull body, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe of a wandring minde? <hi>Atque hi ſunt manes quos patimur:</hi> theſe are the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which we ſuffer in all ages, ſin, and ſorrow, and folly, vexation and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit. Hence ſpring complaints and diſcontent, either for want, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, or the fruſtration of our hopes, or ſome other euill. No proſperitie without change, and in the midſt of laughter the heart is heauie. What way and courſe of life can a man cut out, wherein there
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13672:29"/>is not trouble and vexation of ſpirit? Theologie neuer ſo full of queſtions, the law as full of difficulties as men of quarrels. Phyſicke as manifold in cures as the appetite in abſurd deſires. In Courts few proſper, and thoſe that proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per periſh. The Countrey makes beaſts, and the Citie Diuels. Single life is ſolitarie, and marriage ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>This is the miſerie of life. Now followes the life of Miſerie. Who knowes not that life, and all the comforts of life, they bee but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of afffliction to thoſe that are plunged in griefe? What pleaſure is there in melodie to a man that mournes? And to him that is in an ague, how vnſeaſonable is the diſcourſe of loue and iollitie. Eternitie of torment is the hell of hell: ſo continuance, or life in miſerie, there is the miſery of miſery. Space of time diminiſhes ſorrow that is paſt, but increaſeth that which is preſent, becauſe it weakens patience, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs the hope of deliuerance. Therefore the Patriarch complaines that his dayes were few and euill. Not euill and few.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13672:30"/>For to haue a ſhort time allotted him, and yet euill dayes intermixed, is more euill. But being afflicted with euill yeares, to haue them ſhortened, is leſſe euill. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. O daies few and euill, briefe and tedious. How it lies vpon vs beloued, to lengthen them by good deeds. And ſo much the more becauſe the ſhorteſt of the yeare is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, but the ſhorteſt of our life is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. Let vs fruſtate the tenure of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie, and in euery age doe the vertue of the age, not the ſinne of the age; that ſo not liuing after cuſtome, but after truth, nor making profuſion of the bloud of CHRIST, that it may not faile vs at our greateſt neede, wee may preſerue the ſeale of our redemption inuiolate, and bee bold euery one of vs to pray: O my GOD, let not the end of my deuotion bee ſuddaine, but after much mortification of heart, and long conſumption of languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſires to ſee thee, make a ripe diſſolution of my fleſh and ſpirit, cloſe vp my wearied thoughts, and receiue mee to thy mercie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:13672:30"/>
Liue ſweete IESV, and reigne with the Father, and Holy Ghoſt, one God, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Sermon,</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13672:31"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON. <hi>Of the loue of Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. PET. 1.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whom you loue though yee haue not ſeene.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT which bleſſed Saint <hi>Peter</hi> commends in the diſperſed Iewes of Aſia, Pontus, Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, that they loued Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whom they had not ſeene. The ſame is the praiſe of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Catholickes, who haue liued theſe many yeares, that being ſcattered from ſea to ſea, vnder euery ſtarre, and throughout all lands, yet they loue their one Head vnſeene; as they loue their many fellow-members vnſeene. Which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13672:31"/>is a ſingular commendation in the Daughter of Chriſt diſperſed, His eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed Church, ſo deerely to affect Him whom Shee neuer ſaw: Whereas the daughters of men make ſight a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry antecedent of affection, and will eſteeme highly of no obiect vntill the eye haue ſet a price of it.</p>
            <p>This word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(though)</hi> contained in the aduerbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or elſe vnderſtood, not expreſſed in the originall: implies ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loue of Chriſt; namely, as hee was viſible in the ſtate of Mortality, making that to be the greater, but this the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. As if hee ſhould ſay: You loue Chriſt whom you haue not ſeene; How much more vehement would your loue haue beene if you had ſeene him? Theſe then be the two parts of my Text: Firſt, the loue of Chriſt being ſeene: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the loue of Chriſt being not ſeene. If any man loue not our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, let him be <hi>Anathema Maran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atha.</hi> Of all the ſenſes there is none ſo proper a mediator of loue, as is the ſight: It is the beginning of loue, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Prouerb, <hi>exaſpectu naſcitur amor:</hi> and it is the perfection thereof,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13672:32"/>whilſt we deſire to ſee that whereof we haue much read, or heard. Therefore we loue our eves aboue all parts of our body, giuing them the names of the moſt louely creatures in the world: as the Sunne and Moone: <hi>O oculi gemiua ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deva:</hi> And that which wee loue deereſt wee compare it to the eye: as, <hi>Ocule, ocelle ni;</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Keepe mee as the apple of an eye.</hi> Now the cauſes why ſight ſo much procureth loue. Firſt, it is the moſt ſpirituall ſenſe, and may bee called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a corporall minde, whereby we vnderſtand things ſenſible. By reaſon of which affinity, <hi>videre</hi> is put for <hi>intelligere:</hi> For this cauſe the mind beſt liketh that obiect which is commended to her by the eye. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is the quickeſt ſenſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth ſooneſt fire the affections: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, <hi>Segnius irritant animos immiſſa per aures, quam quae ſunt oculis ſubiecta ſidelibus.</hi> Thirdly, it is the ſureſt euidence, and moſt certaine demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Whence, by metaphor, the word demonſtration is drawne: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fruition of eternall happineſſe is called Viſion. Laſtly, it is the moſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13672:32"/>vnwearied, and vnſatiable ſenſe; the eye being neuer ſatisfied with ſeeing. Which makes for the continuance of loue. For loue hateth nothing more then mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and faſtidious inconſtancie. For theſe cauſes, I ſay, ſight is the moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Factor for Loue.</p>
            <p>Now that wee may the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this loue of Chriſt which they had that ſaw him in the fleſh: let vs conſider a little of the diuers kindes of loue.</p>
            <p>There is a ſenſuall loue, or rather luſt, which the baſe Iewes, nor other Infidels, euer ſuſpected in Chriſt Ieſus, although hee loued the two ſacred ſiſters of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thania;</hi> and though Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> leaned in his boſome, and many woemen vſed to accompany him: therefore the malicious Iewes, amongſt all their falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, durſt not offer to ſtaine his credite with the leaſt ſuſpition of any folly. There is another loue riſing from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſence of the eye, which is not luſt, but curioſitie: When men deſire to ſee rare, or ſtrange things, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefite but to ſatisfie the eye. Such loue, no doubt, had many of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13672:33"/>Iewes, who deſired to ſee Ieſus for his fame and wonders, but with a naturall and humane loue. Other loues there be whereof ſome bee lawfull, ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull; ſome ſenſuall, ſome intellectuall; but all naturall and humane. But the loue which wee enquire after, is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and ſacred; yet much communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with ſenſe and affection. For the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding whereof, I muſt premiſe theſe.</p>
            <p>I haue obſerued a double loue of God. There is a kind of loue which is holy, but meerely ſpirituall; when the ſoule being a ſpirit loueth the Father of Spirits, in ſpirit: abſtracting all media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of body, and bodily accident, vſing no helpe of imagination, or any ſenſe: But conſidering him to bee an eternall Goodneſſe, Incorporeall, Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Authour of all being, and of all good. Whereupon the will doth immediately embrace this obiect of Goodneſſe, reſteth her ſelfe in the loue, and delight thereof. This loue will haue no communion with ſenſe, or any imagination drawne from ſenſe, or any affection, accounting them to bee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13672:33"/>perturbations, and ſtaines of this ſincere delight. This religious loue is more contemplatiue, and therefore in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in men of knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, nouriſhed by viſion, and by diſcourſe. To this the <hi>Platonicks</hi> ſpeake proportionably, who were eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the moſt Theologicall Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. They making the perfection of mans felicity to conſiſt in this intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue: and, as I may ſay, abſtracted ideall delight: ſpend much inke in blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and diſpraiſing bodily and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things: calling them ſhadowes of things ſpirituall, images, and not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, obſcurers of the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: And the body to bee the ſepulcher of the ſoule, and the affections to bee as the rebellious rogues, and vnquiet mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>There is another kind of ſacred loue which is placed in the affections, being not meerely ſpirituall, but making vſe of all ſenſible obiects, for the enſlaming thereof. Thus wee loue God whilſt wee conſider the excellent beauty of all his creatures, giuing him the eminencies of them all; and turning our affections
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13672:34"/>from euery creature to burne towards him which is the Authour of all theſe. And this is moſt properly called deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nouriſhed by ſenſe, and ſenſible accidents: without which no Religion of any Age, or Nation, euer flouriſhed. Wherefore the moſt wiſe God knowing man by nature, to haue ſo much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce with body and bodily things, ordained ſo many Ceremonies, and Sacraments, in his worſhip: And, at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſent his Sonne in the viſible forme of a man, that Hee being Spirit and fleſh, both theſe, our loues, both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and caruall might bee ſpent on him. That our affections might haue ſomething to feede on, as well as our vnderſtandings. And this is the loue whereof the Apoſtle heere ſpeakes which was in the Saints that ſee Chriſt in the fleſh: Which is ſeated in the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and is called deuotion. And ſurely, if wee looke into the examples of piety, and deuotion, in all times, you ſhall finde that the moſt holy and pious men, were men of the moſt hotteſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: as the Prophets, as King <hi>Dauid,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who after their loues
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13672:34"/>were diuerted from doting vpon vanity, and worldly ſhadowes. They out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtripped all men in the ardencie of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, as their Writings and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons witneſſe: breathing nothing but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Ex intimis viſceribus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligam te demine:</hi> And S. <hi>Auſtens</hi> Workes to a iudicious Reader, will plainely ſhew, that though hee bee the moſt profound Father, yet hee ſpeakes more out of his heart, then his head, full of actionate deuotion, euen then when the ſubiect of his Diſcourſe is ſubtilty and vnderſtanding. Hence it is, that woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bee called the deuoute Sexe, by reaſon of the feruencie of their loue: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, <hi>Thy loue to mee was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull paſſing the loue of woemen.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of excepting the mother of God, amongſt thouſand others, the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent examples be <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Egyptian: Which two holy women, the one hauing ſeene Chriſt, the other the place where hee was crucified, they changed their lewd luſts, for hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and incorruptible loue: they waſhed their wanton eyes with teares: And for the latter, her whole fleſh
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13672:35"/>which had beene fired with luſt, ſhee ſacrificed it an whole burnt-offering vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, exhaling it with faſting and penance vntill her dying day. Laſtly, deuout old age, which after much dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and loſſe of grace, would gladly preſerue the relique of deuotion: they keepe it in the warmth of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as appeareth by their tenderneſſe to Religion, often weeping, faſting, and Almeſ-deeds. This being ſo naturall a ground, that deuotion eſpecially confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in affection, and that affections are chiefly moued by ſenſible obiects, and bodily exerciſe: Therefore all Religions neceſſarily haue Ceremonies, and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of this kind: Some profitable, ſome neceſſary, ſome ſuperſtitious. For the eye, as goodly Temples, ornaments of pictures, veſtures, and ſuch like. Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick for the eare.
<note place="margin">See Caluin. Inſtit. q. 4. c. 10</note> Set times of faſting, prayers, offering, and other outward actions: The ruine whereof ouerthrowes deuotion.
<note place="margin">See the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall note in the Geneua Bible.</note> Hither you may referre Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories and Metaphors, which bee the greateſt part of cloquence in Sermons, and bee nothing elſe but ſpeaking pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuers, according to that <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Before
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13672:35"/>whoſe eyes Chriſt Ieſus was deſcribed cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with in you.</hi> Seeing then that theſe things cannot bee gaine-ſaid; How ill do they deſerue of Chriſtianity, who delight in nothing ſo much as ruines of Churches, Church Orders, and Church Ceremonies. They place no more holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in a Temple then a Schoole-houſe; Counſell them to faſt, they anſwer they faſt from ſinne; Tell them of ſitting bare at Diuine Seruice, they anſwere, all things are vncouered before God. They giue no honour to the Sacraments; bid them kneele at the entring into a Church, and when they receiue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euchariſt, they anſwere, they bow the knees of the heart. They offer no other ſacrifice but the calues of their lippes. Inſteed of Almes, they giue poore men good counſell, as if men could cate precepts, and drinke good counſell. They are affected with the ſight of no ſacred Monument. Nay, if our Sauiour himſelfe were aliue they would not go farre to ſee him, or not haue worſhipped him for feare of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Hence comes it thar they haue ſo common a conceit of the bleſſed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13672:36"/>Virgine that bare him in her wombe; that they giue ſo little priuiledge to the Apoſtles that eate and drunke with him: Finally, to any holy place where hee walked, or any Saint to whom hee appeared. They would hold it no hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to haue touched the hemme of his garment. Then <hi>Nathaniel</hi> was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe who deſired to ſee Ieſus, and little <hi>Zacheus</hi> who climed the Tree to looke downe vpon him that was higher then the skie: Then the Wiſe men of the Eaſt were not worthy of that name, who came ſo farre to ſee him. Saint <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> might haue made a better wiſh then aboue all things to haue ſeene Chriſt in the fleſh. But our Sauiour himſelfe condemnes theſe men, when he ſaith; <hi>the Queene of Saba ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt this Generation, for ſhee came farre to heare the wiſedome of</hi> Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>and behold a greater then</hi> Salomon <hi>is heere.</hi> And <hi>Luke</hi> 10.25. <hi>Bleſſed are the eyes that haue ſeene what you ſee: for I ſay vnto you many Prophets haue deſired to ſee that which you ſee, and could not ſee it:</hi> Which is ment of ſeeing Chriſt Ieſus in his mortall eſtate. <hi>Foelix qui potuit
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13672:36"/>fontem boni viſero lucidum:</hi> To apply that ſpeech vnto this ſence. If the eye of a man were ſuddenly made able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Heauens, the Sun, and Moone, and Starres, in their iuſt ſplendure, and bigneſſe: Or to ſee the whole earth with all the creatures in it, at once: <hi>Vuo &amp; diſtincto intuitu:</hi> How would his mind bee rapt with admiration? But the ſight of God manifeſted in the fleſh, was a farre more admirable obiect, the exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of men and Angels, and as I may ſay the proper end why the eye was created. Of which fight, if the ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creatures had beene made capable, How, thinke you, would the Sunne haue deſired to ſhine continually in that cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate where Hee breathed: And the other parts of the earth haue contended that they alſo might haue receiued the impreſſion of His ſacred feete, enuying the felicity of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then let all true Chriſtians honour the happy memories of thoſe bleſſed Saints, who were ordained to ſee that Iuſt One, and to bee eye-witneſſes of that Myſterie, into which the immate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Angels do delight to pry. And as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13672:37"/>for vs, wee that had not that preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to ſee him in the fleſh, yet for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our deuotion, let vs euer beare Him in our fancies, and vſe all meanes that wee may ſeeme to ſee him, that with a readier paſſage wee may feele him, and beare him in our hearts. This is the recompence of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and onely ſolace vnto true loue, by imagination to fill vp the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time and place, and transforme things paſt into things preſent. <hi>Quem vidiſtis paſtores?</hi> whom ſaw yee ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards? tell vs, tell vs. We ſaw the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent infant, and Angels worſhip him. But where? and when? and how? tell mee ſome circumſtance that I may ſeeme to ſee him. <hi>Vidimus Deum parvu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pannis inuolutum, matrem vbera ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouentem.</hi> Wee ſaw God a little one, ſwadled and lying in a cribbe, and his mother giuing him ſuck. O happy ſight! O vnſpeakeable myſterie. <hi>O gratiſſimi vagitus per quos eternos ploratus euaſimus! O foelices pannim, quibus peccatorum ſordes abſterſimus! O praeſepe ſplendidum vbi iacuit panis angelorum. Lacta Maria creatorem tuum, lacta virgo glorieſa. O foelicia oſcula
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13672:37"/>lactentis labijs impreſſa.</hi> It is S. <hi>Auſtens</hi> meditation. <hi>Sapientia ſi oculis cerneretur quantos amores excitaret ſui?</hi> Wiſedome (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) if it could be ſeene with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes, how would it ſtirre vp men to loue it? But the wiſedome of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came viſible and manifeſted in the fleſh, and how ſhould it ſtirre vp men to loue it? This did ſo inflame the beloued Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, him which dranke wiſedome our of the boſome of our Lord, that his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle which is wholly precepts of loue, hee beginnes with, mention of ſeeing Chriſt, and repeates the ſame word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe. <hi>That which wee haue ſeene with our eyes, which wee haue looked vpon, and our hands haue handled of the word of life. For the life appeared, and we haue ſeene it, and it appeared: that I ſay which wee haue ſeene and heard, declare wee vnto you.</hi> And the whole number of the twelue, when after his laſt farewell hee aſcended, how ſtood they gazing on him, as being loth to looſe the laſt minute of his viſible preſence. And no maruell: for the very ſight, no doubt, conueighed vnto the faithfull, a benigne influence prefigured in the old Teſtament, where to looke
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13672:38"/>ſtedfaſtly vpon the braſen Serpent, was ſoueraigne againſt the poyſonfull ſting of fierie Serpents. What deuout Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an now liuing, would not giue the whole world if he had it, for to ſee him? To ſee him either in his childe-hood, or in in his youth, in his humilitie, or in his maieſtie. When it pleaſed him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make his glorious deitie ſhine through his man-hood, as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> thinkes he did when he called S. <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Andrew,</hi> who therefore preſently laid away and followed him. Heare the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the bleſſed Father S. <hi>Auſten</hi> vpon this poynt. <hi>Hei mihi quia videre non potui Dominum angelorum, heu quod tam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeſtimabili pietati preſens obſtupeſcere non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rui.</hi> And further. <hi>Cur ô anima, &amp;c.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ô my ſoule, waſt thou not preſent that thou mightſt haue beene pierced through with ſharpeſt griefe, when thy Sauiours ſide was pierced with a ſpeare? where thou couldſt not haue endured to haue ſeene the hands and feet of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker rent with nailes: that thou mightſt haue ſwounded to haue ſeene the bloud of thy redeemer ſpilt, that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt haue condoled with the bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13672:38"/>O gracious good Lady, what ſtreames of teares may I thinke flowed out of thy moſt chaſte eyes when thou beheldedſt thy innocent, thy onely ſon bound, ſcourged, murdered, fleſh of thy fleſh, &amp; bone of thy bone ſo cruelly cut &amp; mangled. And further, <hi>vtina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum felice Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſepho dominum meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de cruce depoſuiſſem, cur non fui deoſculatus loca vulnerum? &amp;c.</hi> Thus holy men were wont to incenſe their loue, and their deuotion, to cleanſe their imaginations from the idols of carnall beautie, which hauing entred at the eyes haunt the diſquiet fancies of poore youth, and cannot be ſpelled, nor expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but with the image of God incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe our venerable ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors from all clymates of the Chriſtian world, haue reſorted to the holy Cittie, that although they could not ſee their Sauiour, yet they might ſee and worſhip where his feete had trode or walked, where he wept, and ſwet, and bled, and died. There was the price of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion numbred, that earth and that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhal witneſſe, that there the ſumme was tendered, and that innocent heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloud
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13672:39"/>powred out, which none can powre into his breaſt againe. This made good <hi>Paula,</hi> and her daughter <hi>Euſtochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> Romane Ladies of the honourable family of the <hi>Grachi,</hi> remoue with all their ſubſtance to <hi>Bethleem,</hi> and there they liued, and there they died with S. <hi>Ierom.</hi> This made S. <hi>Helen</hi> honour of our Engliſh nation, the happy mother of great <hi>Conſtantioe,</hi> ſo deuoutly to viſite euery place where our Lord conuerſed, and euery where to erect ſo many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memories, ſo many goodly Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. This cauſed S. <hi>Ierom</hi> to ſpend the greateſt part of his life there. There hee commented, there he indited, there hee tranſlated. And for this cauſe many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuines, amongſt whom S. <hi>Ierom</hi> &amp; <hi>Euſebius,</hi> with diuers of late memorie, haue carefully deſcribed all the ſacred places, and religious monuments of the Holy land, that thoſe which haue not ſeene them really, might ſee them ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarily, and nouriſh their Diuine cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations without ſupeſtition, without any great coſt, or trouble: I that they might ſee <hi>Canaan</hi> a farre off, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did from mount <hi>Phaſga.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:13672:39"/>
Now looke what hath been ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning deuotion nouriſhed by ſight, the ſame is true likewiſe of the other learned ſenſe, namely, hearing, as the hearing of muſicke, or eloquent diſcourſe, which being vſed without curious ſcrupuloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and affectation, how greatly they increaſe the loue of God, and of his true worſhip, it appeares to any liberall and ingenious diſpoſition, vnleſſe any man thinke the vſe of muſicke proper to ſtirre vp vanity, to nouriſh pleaſure, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine lightneſſe and obſcenitie. And not</p>
            <p n="1">1 To raiſe vp mens minds to meditation of heauenly ioyes, whereof muſick may ſeeme a kinde of type.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To confider the harmonie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the world, how all Ages, all Nations, all Languages praiſe Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Out of the mouthes of Babes ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings hee prepareth praiſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 To expiate the eares which haue beene polluted by wanton madrigals, and laſciuious ditties.</p>
            <p n="5">5 To kindle the affections with loue of God.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Laſtly, to praiſe him with learned hymnes, who is the giuer of all excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13672:40"/>Vnleſſe any man thinke that elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence was giuen naturally to adorne folly, and flatteries, to ouerthrow right, to colour falſhood, and deceaue ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and to be miſvſed, when it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliyed to ſtrengthen truth, to ſweeten diligence, and commend pietie. <hi>Quis ita deſipiat vt hoc ſapiat?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> 4. <hi>de Dectrina. Chr.</hi> And if any man obiect that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue himſelfe concerning the lawfull vſe of artificiall Muſicke in Churches, it is falſe: For though hee ſpeakes of his owne experience, that the delight of his ſenſe did ſometimes preuaile aboue reaſon; yet hee confeſſes the excellent vſe of Muſick for deuotion. And for being too ſcrupulous hee checkes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, calling it <hi>nimia ſeueritas;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that hee approues the cuſtome of the Church: <hi>Vt per oblectamenta aurium infirmior animus in affectum pietatis aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat:</hi> That by delight of the eare, the weake minde of man might riſe vp into pious affections: whereof hee makes himſelfe an example, with delightſome remembrance how hee was moued to teares at the hearing of artificiall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13672:40"/>Church Muſicke: <hi>Cum reminiſcor lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas quas fudi ad cantus eccleſiae tuae, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam inſtituti huius vtilitatem agnoſco:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith there of artificiall muſicke, may bee as well an argument againſt plaine ſong, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon tunes in Churches, which affect ſome men as much, and of many are ſung with as great affectation. Againe, if for this difficulty, they would wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the lawfull vſe of muſicke, let them reade the two chapters next going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; they ſhal find that he maketh the ſame difficulty in the vſe of all the ſenſes, which if they will refuſe therefore, then muſt they neither ſee, nor ſmell, nor eate, nor drinke. But this holy man there expreſſes his carefulneſſe to auoide ſin; as alſo did Saint <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> whom hee there citeth. But how farre their ſpirit was from preiudicing others, or from ſcrupling mens conſciences in the vſe of the approued Inſtitutions of the Church, their other ſpeeches and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſufficient witneſſes. Wherefore to ſhorten this diſcourſe, let vs all ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to haue a zealous and deuout loue of Chriſt; both that which riſeth out
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13672:41"/>of knowledge and vnderſtanding, and that which riſeth out of ſenſe and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And to this purpoſe vſe all thoſe meanes which the practiſe of moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers. and the law of Nature her ſelfe doth warrant: which is not ſenſuall loue, but affectionate, and holy, raiſed out of ſenſe. As they which ſaw Chriſt loued him the more, not for the linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his body; but being enflamed with conſideration that they ſhould ſee their Creator become Fleſh, who is in his owne Nature inuiſible. That they ſhould ſee the ſame paſſions as in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in him which was Impaſſible: and all their owne infinrmities without deformitie of ſinne: That man might not now chuſe but loue God, vnleſſe he would not loue himſelfe: This, I ſay, bred admiration and loue in them, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall loue, yet raiſed out of ſenſe, and is chiefe part of that which wee proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call deuotion.</p>
            <p>And thus much of the firſt part of my Text; namely, the loue of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeene: Where I haue ſhewed how much ſight augmenteth loue: And how all other ſenſible meanes and externall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13672:41"/>practiſes are incitements and inuitations to encreaſe deuotion. Deuotion, which is the onely happineſſe of this life, and to be preferred before wiſedome, ſubtilty, or diſcourſe, being indeed the end and perfection of all. The delicious taſte of heauenly ioyes, which God giues vnto his Saints here, that they may long after the fruition of the whole: Whereof Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeakes in the 40 chap. of the 10. booke of his Confeſſions: <hi>Et aliquando intromittis me Domine in affectum multum inuſitatum introrſum ad neſcio quam dulcedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quaeſi perficiatur in me neſcio quid erit, quod vita iſta non erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond part, which is the loue of Chriſt not ſeene: <hi>Quem cum non videritis diligitis: whom yee loue, though yee haue not ſeene.</hi> This, not onely S. <hi>Peter</hi> heere, but S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, with many other Worthies haue admired; to ſee how ſoone the world, without compulſion, conſented to follow, and to loue Him whom they neuer ſaw: How ſo many thouſands and millions were moued with ſuch a ſtrange inſtinct, to leaue their goods, their wiues, their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, parents, their deereſt Country:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13672:42"/>and laſtly, to looſe their liues ſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for loue of him whom they neuer ſaw. This amazed the vnbeleeuing world, to ſee her number daily miniſhed, and moſt furious perſecutors become the hotteſt louers. What ſecret influence ſo raigned in mens hearts? what cruel loue made them ſo impatient that they ranne ſhowting to their death? Wherefore forſooke they all their preſent ioyes, which they not onely ſaw, but caryed in their eyes, to loue him whom they ſaw not? Crying, <hi>Hunc amemus, huno amemus.</hi> Nothing could bribe them, or abalienate their mindes. Youth was not moued with beauty, nor old age with money, nor children with feare of death, nor Stateſ-men with prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: No contumelies, no diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces preuailed, they ſuffered all things, they endured all things, and all this for the loue of him whom they neuer ſaw. The new married preferred the graue before the bed. Honourable and beautifull maides chooſe rather to bee called virgins of Chriſt, then queenes to great Princes. The fraile ſexe was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Martyrdome, and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13672:42"/>mothers ouercomming nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held with cheerefull countenance their ſwete infants killed for the loue of Chriſt, as wee read of that happy childe which died with the conſtant martyr <hi>Romanus.</hi> How willingly his mother gaue him to the hands of the tormentor; kiſſing him but once, which was as little as a mother could doe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nee immorata eſt fletibus tantum oſculum</l>
               <l>Impreſſit vnum, vale, ait, dulciſſime,</l>
               <l>Et eum beatus regna Chriſti intraueris</l>
               <l>Memento matris.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now if a man inquire into the inward mouing cauſe for which the world was ſo ſtrangely carried away with affection vnto Chriſt, hee ſhall find it to bee faith. Which faith though the Scripture op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to viſion, yet calleth it a kinde of ſight. So faithfull <hi>Abraham</hi> deſired to ſee Chriſts day, and ſaw it, and reioyced. By faith <hi>Moſes</hi> indured patiently as if he had ſeene the inuiſible. And by the eye of faith all the Saints ſince the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing them that ſaw him, haue loued him as firmly as if themſelues had ſeene him. They ſeeing the head, beleeued of the body: wee ſeeing the body, beleeue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13672:43"/>concerning the head. <hi>Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habet fides oculos ſuos, quibus quodammodo videt verum eſſe quod nondum videt.</hi> For faith hath it eyes, whereby in ſome manner it ſees that to be true, which as yet it ſees not, ſaith S. <hi>Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Faith is oppoſed to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall view of things viſible, and to the demonſtratiue knowledge of things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible. Which knowledge is alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led intuitiue knowledge. Now the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſight of Chriſt in his humilitie, was onely proper to them that liued in his time. Though by imagination wee can likewiſe repreſent vnto our ſelues the ſame. But the ſight of his ſpirituall and glorified body ſhall be the reward of all. And as for the intelligible viſiun of invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible glory of the Godhead of Chriſt, and of the eternall Trinitie; they that ſee it here in twy-light, ſhall then behold it as at noone day, and loue it there with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable feruencie of ſpirit, if they continue here in that modell of warmth which this life affoordeth. The hope whereof how greatly doth it ſuſtaine the patience of his abſence, and confirme the conſtancy of louing Chriſt vnſeene, when we haue ſo good aſſurance to ſee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13672:43"/>his ſpirituall body, and that happineſſe which neuer eye hath ſeene? Where if he ſhew his fiue wounds, and the veritie of all which hee did and ſuffered in this life, what can be wanting to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that which is in part, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting faith into viſion?</p>
            <p>Meane while wonderfull is that grace which makes vs now to loue him. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the conuerſion of the world, the ſtrange preſeruation of the Catholicke Church, the authoritie of the ſame Church, the bloud of ſo many Martyrs, the fulfilling of Prophecies, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent learning of Catholicke Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Catholick Gouernours, with many other vnanſwerable arguments, haue in a manner demonſtrate the whole truth of Chriſtian Religion: Inſomuch that hee which will not now beleeue without ſeeing wonders, is himſelfe a wonder, ſaith S. <hi>Auſten.</hi> Yet in many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges when God hath permitted generall inundations of <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> of <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Saracens</hi> ouer the Chriſtian world, which the old ſerpent hauing ſpued out of his mouth, deſired to make <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the woman to bee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13672:44"/>carried away of the floud; or when fearefull tempeſts of hereſie doe obſcure the Church, that for a time neither Sunne nor moone appeare, till controuerſies bee determined, till ancient records bee ſe arched, and vnquiet noueliſts ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the ſafeſt way was alwayes to caſt himſelfe into the boſome of the Church, that faith might ſupport where knowledge failes, and the loue of Chriſt continue, where he was not ſeene.</p>
            <p>Faith is the ſubſiſtence of matters ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, and the euidence of things not ſeene, by the firme embracing whereof in the midſt of all miſerable temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and inueſtigable errours, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full louers of Chriſt Ieſus haue loued him whom they neuer ſaw neither with the eye of ſenſe, nor the eye of reaſon. Great friendſhip hath there beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt men which neuer ſaw one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faces, yet true report of wiſedome and vertue hath bred ſtrange coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and familiaritie of mindes, as if their ſoules had met together in the night when their bodies reſted: or becauſe that mindes being incorporeall, neede not viſible preſence to vnite them, nor
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13672:44"/>are their loues ſeparated by diſtance of place. Which if it be true in natural loue, and humane affection, how much more certaine is it in ſpirituall and Diuine? where not onely ſimilitude of nature combines, but alſo vnitie of ſpirit. If thou loueſt none but whom thou ſeeſt (ſaith S. <hi>Auſten</hi>) then ſhouldſt thou not loue thy ſelfe. <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim teipſum niſi in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo vides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many men there be, whoſe wiſdome will not ſuffer them to bee credulous, their hands haue eyes, and their hearts haue eyes: they beleeue that which they ſee, and they will loue that which they ſee: vnknowne vnbeleeued, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene vnloued. But vnto the moſt of faithfull Chriſtians, Almightie God hath left more things to bee beleeued then knowne, that there might bee place for reward. For hope that is ſeene, is no hope. Euery one could not liue at that time when Chriſt was liuing, nor ſee the wonders which he wrought, or which his Prophets did before him, or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles after him. Yet many will ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, if we had liued in thoſe times, or if whe had talked with one riſen from the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13672:45"/>dead, we had ſurely repented. Indeede the <hi>Tyrians</hi> &amp; <hi>Sidonians,</hi> if they had ſeene the miracles at <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> they would haue turned their purple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſackcloth: but they had ſufficient helpes, and ſo haſt thou: neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou whether thou mightſt be ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, through thine owne firſt wilfull negligence, that the ſight of Chriſt wold haue cauſed no more loue in thee, then it did in <hi>Herod,</hi> who defired of long to ſee him, and not beleeuing <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, neither wouldeſt thou beleeue if one ſhould riſe from the dead. S. <hi>Auſten</hi> ſayes hee was often tempted to deſire a ſigne from God concerning him ſelfe; but by Gods grace he alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted that temptation. So our Sauiour taxeth the Gentleman of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> whoſe ſonne was ſick at <hi>Capernaum, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you ſee ſignes and wonders you will in no wayes beleeue.</hi> The Atheiſt if he might ſee the Diuell, he would hate him. And the Idolater, if hee may haue a palpable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, hee will worſhip him. <hi>Make vs Gods to goe before vs,</hi> cry the Iſraelites, as if things that were inuifible, were not. They that deſire to ſee the holy Cittie,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13672:45"/>vpon diſtruſt or curioſitie, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the eye, or dwelling farre off, greatly indanger their preſent eſtate, their fame, their liues, and neglect their neceſſary functions. I ſee not how they can warrant that action. Againſt which S. <hi>Gregorie Niſſen</hi> ſpeakes in an Epiſtle of his. <hi>Locall motiou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>makes thee not neerer vnto God, which is in all places. And it is better to goe a pilgrimage from thy body to God, then from thy countrey to Iurie: for whilſt wee are at home with the body, wee are ſteangers vnto God. Ieruſalem is not now the neceſſary place of worſhip, the word is neere thee, and euery faithfull ſoule is Ieruſalem.</hi> For as goodly vineyard which coſt the Husbandman much care, and his ſervants long labour, being the ſweeteſt plot of ground which hee could chuſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the indulgence of the heauens, and all the elements to cheriſh it, whilſt it was tender, and flouriſhed, and at the time of vintage all men reſorted thither, to ſee the beauty and temperate ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to reape the fruit which grew not elſe where: but after the fruite was gathered, the hedges being broken, and the ſwine hauing defaced it, and other
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13672:46"/>beaſts haunting it, though the Winter beautie thereof be louely, yet the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of comming thither it aboliſhed, and the conuenience of ſeeing is much limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: So Ieruſalem that pleaſant Citty of God, where the word of life grew, ſo watred by Prophets, ſo watched by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, during the beautie and glory of her ſummer age, thither the Tribes came vp, and from all Countries there they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: but when the fulneſſe of time was come, wherein the grapes of this holy vine were preſſed, and the bloud thereof conueighed by Apoſtles and Euangeliſts throughout the world, to cheare the hearts euen of the coldeſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Ieruſalem became <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Prophet ſpeaketh, no longer neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and though euer holy and reuerend, yet often dangerous to be viſited, being polluted by wilde infidels, and now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of vnchriſtened Turkes. The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard of <hi>Balſamon</hi> is remoued from the Hilles of <hi>Engaddi</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſo ſaluation, which was only of the Iewes, is now tranſlated to the Gentiles, <hi>Et Aſſyrium vulgo naſcitur amomum.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then, although the moſt worthy
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13672:46"/>and deuoute Chriſtians haue increaſed their deuotion and pietie by ſight of the holy monuments at Ieruſalem, yet many who neuer ſaw them, haue beene more godly then ſome others that haue ſeene them, and beleeue as firmely, and loue Chriſt Ieſus their redeemer as deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as if they had ſeene him, or ſeene the place where he was ſeene. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For (ſayes <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Niſſen</hi>) if thy inward man be full of bad thoughts, although thou ſtandeſt vpon Golgotha, or mount Oliuet, or vnder the monument of his reſurrection, thou art as farre from Chriſt, as they which neuer acknowledged him. The ſame is true of all ſenſible meanes, and outward actions, which if they bee not ioyned with ſinceritie of the ſpirit, they are vnprofitable to vs, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtfull to the father of ſpirits. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are content to performe theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall actions, which they do <hi>perfuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> meerely for faſhion, without any tincture of ſpirit: Eſpecially where there is a multitude of ceremonies, as in the Romane Church, and in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of the Eaſterne Churches, is moſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13672:47"/>apparant. Wee are all by nature ready to chuſe that which is of eafier perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: and in actions, &amp; matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which of all others are moſt tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe they touch the conſcience, the crafty Mind would gladly reſt her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and thinke to diſcharge all by light workes of the body, and of the ſenſes. <hi>Is this the faſt which I haue choſen,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>for a man to bow his necke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weake with abſtinence, to put on ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes: Is this the faſt which I haue choſon? Nay, is not this the faſt which I haue choſen, to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, and to let the oppreſſed go free? and to deale thy bread vnto the hungry:</hi> Where God hates the outward obedience, if it bee without faſting from ſinne. And in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, better ſpirituall worſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out externall, then externall without that which is ſpirituall. So hee ſaith, <hi>Rend your hearts and not your garments. And I will haue mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> Where the aduerbe is a Comparatiue rather then a Negatiue: And therefore the Septu. well tranſlate it: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ſub <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. God forbids neither, nay hee commands
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13672:47"/>both; but preferres the one before the other. So many, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> they will eate no fleſh in Lent, but they will bite and deuoure their brethren: They will drinke no wine, but they will drink iniquity like water. What profites it to bee pale with faſting, and at the ſame time to bee leane with hatred, and euuy? What profites it if wee abſtaine from fleſh, which is ſometime lawfull, and do thoſe things which are neuer lawfull? therefore I ſay with Scripture, and with holy Fathers, that as the preſence and ſight of Chriſt would little haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed loue in his Diſciples, vnleſſe they had alſo ſeene him with the eyes of the inward man: No more doe any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and externall meanes further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, if they bee ſeparated from the inward and ſpirituall motions of the heart <hi>My ſonne giue mee thy heart. Why draweſt thou neere mee with thy lips when thy heart is farre from mee?</hi> To proceed then, though euery one haue not that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretogatiue giuen them to bee Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs; to die for loue of him that died for their ſaluation: Yet ouery one may mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his earthly members, and die to ſin,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13672:48"/>which is a kind of Martirdome. In like manner, though euery one could not ſee Chriſt, and ſo loue him; yet they may loue him whom they haue not ſeene by faith, which is a kind of ſight. Nay, if they which ſaw him, and loued, were ſuch as would not loue him vnleſſe they had ſeene him; greater is their reward that loue him whom they haue not ſeene. For what ſaid our Lord to Saint <hi>Thomas: Thomas becauſe thou ſeeſt, thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueſt; happy are they which beleeue and ſee not.</hi> What remaines now but to prouoke you to the loue of him whom you doe not ſee: who firſt loued you, vnſeene? Nay, when you were worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Whom you hope to ſee, and ſee him as he is. Let mee ſay vnto the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that liue in obſcurity, and miſery, wait till the cloud bee broken, and the Sunne ſhine out. Let mee ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſimple and ignorant, but louing and faithfull: bee conſtant, and you ſhall ſee as you are ſeene. Let mee ſay vnto the wiſe and learned: helpe yee the weak ſighted, and make him louing that is blind. Laſtly, to all men, though you loue him which is vnſeene, yet let
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13672:48"/>your loue bee ſeene. Loue in deed, and not in word: By <hi>this wee know that wee loue him, if wee keepe his Commandements.</hi> If your loues burne vehemently vpon things temporal and viſible; how are you ſaid to loue him whom yee haue not ſeene. Siluer, and gold, and gay appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, ample poſſeſſions, and goodly buildings, faire fleſh and bloud com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of corruptible elements, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer deceiptfull time hath coloured, or the world hath ſet a gloſſe on: if yee bee euer gazing and admiring theſe things, how are yee ſaid to loue him whom you haue not ſeene? When woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men go to ſee, and to bee ſeene: when men, the litle good they do, they do it to be ſeene of men: When moſt had rather ſeeme then bee good: how are they ſaid to loue him whom they haue not ſeene? He that longs to ſee euery ſtrange thing hee heares of, and to haue euery coſtly thing which he ſees, how can this loue of Chriſt bo in him? He which hateth his brother whom he daily ſees, how can hee loue his Sauiour whom hee neuer ſaw? When the concupiſcence of the eye is waxen dimme, and the faire forbidden
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13672:49"/>fruit is faded: Alas, how will yee wiſh that yee had ſeene leſſe, and leſſe loued that yee ſaw, and more loued him whom yee neuer ſaw. Behold him in his members, behold him in his poore diſtreſſed membes; behold him harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and naked, behold him hungry and thirſty: Cloth him, lodge him, feed him, if you loue him: that when you ſhall ſee him comming in the Clouds, with glory, yee may heare, <hi>Come yee bleſſed, for when I was hungry you fed mee, when I was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked you clothed mee.</hi> Which happineſſe Hee grant vs, that liueth and raigneth with the Father, and Holy Ghoſt, to whom bee all praiſe and glory euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the third Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:13672:49"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH SERMON. <hi>Of the frailty of Man.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. PET. 1.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>All fleſh is as graſſe, and all the glory of man as the flower of graſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS is the echo of a cry in the fortieth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> the ſixth verſe, rebounding from the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of <hi>Peter: The voice ſaid cry:</hi> Becauſe all fleſh, the whole world, muſt heare. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whole world is ſo ingurgitate in the dulneſſe of fleſh, that without a cry they, cannot heare: It ſeemes then
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13672:50"/>that God will haue this cry to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>à reſonance,</hi> in our eares, which no melodie of pleaſure ſhould take away. The Heathen man cauſed one to cry daily vnto him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Remember thou art a man. And there are two maine cries in the Scripture: The one puts vs in minde of our immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, which S. <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaith hee heard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſounding in his eares, <hi>Ariſe you dead and come to iudgement.</hi> The ſecond of our mortality, and is of neceſſity precedent to the former, proclaimed by this Harbinger: <hi>Omnis caro foenum: All fleſh is graſſe,</hi> and all the glory of man: Wherefore, hee that hath eares to heare let him heare: 1. the common meanneſſe of his nature, al fleſh is graſſe. <hi>All,</hi> there is the community, <hi>Fleſh,</hi> that is the name of his nature: thirdly, <hi>Graſſe,</hi> there is the meaneneſſe of his nature. In the ſecond part, the meaneneſſe of the excellency of his nature: <hi>The glory of man,</hi> that is the execllency; <hi>The flower of graſſe,</hi> there is the frailty of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Laſtly, without exception <hi>all: all the glory of man is as the flower of the graſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All fleſh is graſſe:</hi> For God hauing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13672:50"/>made all men <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of one bloud, although they haue variety of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet they all meete in this ground that they are graſſe. <hi>I am no better then my fathers,</hi> ſaith <hi>Elias.</hi> And the Apoſtles make themſelues leuell in the ſame vaile of miſerie, with the common people of <hi>Iconium,</hi> that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the ſame ſufferings. For this cauſe the Holy Ghoſt calles the poore mans body the fleſh of the rich. <hi>Deſpiſe not thou thine owne fleſh.</hi> Now the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond poynt is the name of our nature, which is here called fleſh. The body is our worſe halfe, and fleſh the worſe of the worſe: for it is tender, and ſubiect to change and loſſe. Further, the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit. Therfore <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gori</hi> cals it with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this enuious little fleſh. By this name the Scripture calling the body, or the whole man, and vſing the part for the whole, yet would not haue the part to bee the whole: for then we ſhould bee like the Cretians, who were nothing but belly and beaſt: or as the Iſraelites, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to fat their fleſh, the Pſalmiſt ſaith, that God ſent leaneſſe into their ſoules.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13672:51"/>Howſoeuer then you interpret the word fleſh, either of the body, or of the nature and eſtate of man, which confiſteth much of things bodily, or of carnalitie, which is periſhing of the ſoule in fauour of the body. Of all theſe the Prophet cries aloud, <hi>Omnis caro foenum,</hi> all fleſh is graſſe.</p>
            <p>To enter then vpon this argument, which is the graſſie ſubſtance of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, did not the firſt man ſpring out of the earth? and though he grew amongſt the delicious fruits of paradice, and had no poyſon in his roote, yet he continued not in honour, but being tranſplanted into that common where we grow, ſpred his degenerous of-ſpring ouer the whole earth, whoſe ſeed multiplying innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, was nouriſhed with no other food vntill the floud came, and corrupted the vertue thereof. Since which time, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our diet bee changed, and fleſh be nouriſhed with fleſh, yet the chiefe of that fleſh is but graſſe concocted and conuerted into fleſh: and the fleſh of men and beaſts are both reſolued into one duſt, which duſt by perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution in the ſame circuit, ſends forth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13672:51"/>againe that aliment which ſuſtames both them and vs. Before that iuſt and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall deluge had diſcoloured the earth, it ſeemeth probable that as the dayes of man were of a greater length; ſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerable verdure of the earth was of more continuance in all habitable elymates thereof. But after that calamitie imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly in the diſtinction which tho Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty eſtabliſhed, a greater portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was allotted to the harder times, the ſweet ſeaſons of the yeare were contracted, and decaying Autumne, &amp; the aſpetitie of barren Winter prolonged. Agreeably whereunto the ſpaces of our life were meaſured. The yong ſpringall ſoone paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through his greene hopes, and ripe manhood being ſtraightned in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, encroching age extends the reſt in trouble and tempeſt vntill death. There is <hi>Cruda viridiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſenoctus,</hi> whom the Greekes call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who through the indulgence of a milde Winter, beſides the venorable antiquitie of their gray haires, which is the uncture of wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſage experience, haue alſo freſh vigour in their bloud, and actinity in their wittes and vnderſtandings. But
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13672:52"/>for the moſt part the ſtrength of theſe yeares is labour and ſorrow: for it is ſoone cut downe, and with one blaſt of Gods anger they flye away. So the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Champion ſighed to ſee his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere and dead armes: And <hi>Helen</hi> wept when ſhee ſawe her withered beautie in the glaſſe. So that the Philoſophy of nature doth reſtraine our pride, compriſing the progreſſe and perſection of our life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the period of one yeare. <hi>Quale gonus fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum, tale eſt &amp; hominum.</hi> There is a time of growing, and a time of fading: but no part of our time paſſeth out of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. Which affordeth matter of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. For as plants depend vpon the planots, and are more beholding to the Suimne their father, then the Earth their mother: ſo that which we liue, although it be ſupplied by an inward cauſe, like to that power where with the earth was firſt indued by the creating Word; yet the fauour or diſpleaſure of heauen confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more to this effect, then either the natiue facultie within vs, or all our owne induſtry and endeuours. That which we plow, and ſow, and grinde, and bake, it is not our worke, but Gods. So ſings the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13672:52"/>Pſalmiſt: <hi>Hee brings forth bread out of the earth.</hi> Not corne, but bread. What ſhould I ſpeake of the Mildew of Serenes, of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and conſumptions, which like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicular feruours, burne vp our bodies by the rootes? What of blaſting of cankers, and the greene ſickneſſe? all which doth ſhew the ſimilitude of our fleſh with graſſe. The remembrance of which ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall God hath ſigned vpon our heads, whoſe change of colour, and leafe-fall declareth plainly that his body is <hi>Conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ceſpite culmen,</hi> a poore cottage, whoſe toppeds couered with a ſodde of earth. <hi>Earth, earth, earth,</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>earth thou waſt, and earth thou art, &amp; earth thou ſhalt be,</hi> whoſe bones are ſtones whoſe veines are riuers, onely in this it differs; the earth is fixed, and immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, man is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, earth walking vpon earth. Can any cogitation make vs more humble, or more humane? <hi>Humus aut humi repens es.</hi> Graſſe, or graſſe-hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſaith Dinine <hi>Eſay.</hi> Hee ſitteth vpon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are as graſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers. Poore graſhoppers, that ſing care away, merry and pleaſant in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13672:53"/>their ſummer-dayes, and not prouiding for the aduerſity of Winter, and of want. O remember thy Creator before the yeares draw nigh, when thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them. When all the daughters of muſicke ſhall bee brought low, when the Graſhhopper ſhall bee a burthen, <hi>&amp; diſſipabitur capparis,</hi> and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite ſhall faile, when man goeth to his long home, and the mourners goe about the ſtreets, and the voyce ſaith <hi>Cry. what ſhall I cry? All fleſh is graſſe,</hi> and euery man is vanitie. <hi>Vanitie of vanities</hi> (ſaith the preacher) <hi>all is vanitie. Omnis caro,</hi> all; but eſpecially the many, <hi>vere foenum eſt populus,</hi> ſurely the people, which grow ſo triuiall, and ſo innumerable vpon the the face of the earth. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Clemens,</hi> the domeſticals of worldly delight. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Earth liuing, &amp; earth louing, &amp; affecting any thing but truth. <hi>vere foenum eſt populus,</hi> ſurely the people are graſſe: the multiplying multitude, <hi>foecunda paupertas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lucan,</hi> prolifical &amp; fertile poore. Who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be as poore in ſpirit as in ſubſtance, are the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubiect of <hi>Gods</hi> mercy. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13672:53"/>ſaith the mercifull Lord Ieſus, my bowels are tender to this poore mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: but when their ſinnes ſpread as themſelues, luxuriant, and infinite, the diſpleaſure of Almighty, God mowes them downe by whole millions at once, they are troden vnder the feet of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, peſtilence and famine do depopulate great Cities, and for an embleme of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh, graſſe groweth in the ſtreetes. Poore Chriſtian brethren, ſaith S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> you that repleniſh the earth, why do ye cumber the ground? and make the land grone, and lade God with your i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquities, and preſſe him vnder you, as a Cart that is preſſed with ſtraw. Your ſinnes turne you into ſtraw, and know ye not that God is a conſuming fire? For if you luſt, lye, ſweare, purloyne, &amp; will not truſt him for raiment, which clothes the graſſe of the field: you make your ſelues like to that graſſe which is to day, and to morrow is caſt into the ouen. When the root of bitterneſſe ſprings into infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, and thorny cares choake the word, &amp; when that ſaying of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees is verified, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are accurſed being ouer-growne and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13672:54"/>ouer-graſt with thiſtles, and malice, with curſings, with drunkenneſſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther venemous and vitious weeds, what are they but fruites of the firſt maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe end is to bee burnt? Thus <hi>Sodom,</hi> which was greene as the garden of God, whem their ſinnes were ranke, and growne ouer their heads, they were deſtroied with fire from heauen. And the populous Iſraelites, which grew as plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull as the graſſe of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes were ſtrowed in the drie wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of all that preuailing multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but two were planted in the land of Promiſe. Calamitie comes of <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> the conflagration of a whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey like a ſtubble field. And in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian landes, what wofull deſolation hath deuoured the miſerable vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar? As an Oxe licketh vp the graſſe round about him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. Or as the Prouerbe ſpeakes, that where the foote of the grand ſignior his horſe treadeth, nothing will grow that is greene. <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, popule mi,</hi> my people, my people, ſaith Almightie God, <hi>quid potui facere, quodnon feet?</hi> What could I doe for you which I haue not done? I haue watered you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13672:54"/>with the deaw of Heauen, giuing you ſhowers and fruitfull ſeaſons, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing your ſucklings with the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt iuyce, filling your hearts with ioy and gladneſſe, couering your imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions with mercie, and remembring that you were but fleſh. But becauſe you longed for anger, behold your land is left vnto you deſolate.</p>
            <p>Beloued in our Lord, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are theſe things ſo? hath God waſted our brethren, and made way for his wrath through the throngeſt of them, and ſhall wee muſter our ſinnes, and thinke our ſelues as farre remoued from God, as we are diuided from the whole world? when wee ſhall haue beene, ſhall praeterciroumciſed <hi>Saracens,</hi> or other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh locuſts graze on our poſteritie, and deglut our labours? <hi>Barbarus has ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getes?</hi> ſhall barbarous miſcreants ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe fields? ſhall the abhominable Alcora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſupplant our Bibles, or vnknown language bellow in our Churches, or the bodies be proſtrate to infernal <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whoſe knees would not bow to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed name of <hi>Ieſus?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I heare the ſoft murmure of your
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13672:55"/>hearts, God forbid. Then let vs ſeeke Him, before He ſlay vs: and bee not like the Iſraelites, who when He ſlew them, they ſought Him, and ſought Him early, when it was too late. But hitherto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath compared the common frailty of our nature with the ordinarie paſture of the field. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>gramen, aut ſtramen,</hi> graſſe withered, or greene. But is there nothing excellent and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in humane eſtate aboue this? Yes, and that's the ſecond poynt. What is the glory of man? <hi>As the flower of graſſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle; or as the Prophet ſtiles it, <hi>All his goodlineſſe is as the flower of the field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The top of eminence is a crowne, and that's as <hi>Circular,</hi> and of as ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as the crowne of the yeare, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 65. the two great <hi>Caeſars</hi> haue their names in two moneths, which are the ſtrength and glory of the yeare, as they the Maieſty and maturitie of the Romane Empire. Neither was euer knowne more then one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſummer vigor in the period of any king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. What conſtance then in a volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diademe, which being carried about
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13672:55"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the courſe of nature, hath ben tranſlated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cedar to the brier; from the Maiſter to the ſeruant, which proud Popes haue ſpurned from the heads of Princes, and was diſparaged in that Thorny Wrearh that pierced the ſacred temples of our Lord. Roſes and Lillies are the enſignes of this happy Kingdome: long may they flouriſh. For this is the peculiar honour of our ſtate, <hi>Not Salomon in all his royalty was clothed like one of thoſe:</hi> And though the Lillie withered is of no vſe, yet Roſes retaine their ſweetneſſe after death. If ſupreme Potentates, and mighty Monarches of the earth, had conſidered how tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is that felicity whereon they boaſted: then would they haue endeuored, as they were flowers of ornament, ſo to haue bin fruites of benefite to the Country where they grew; but when their chiefe end was to ſhine in admiration, and to draw the eyes of the world vpon the colour of their preſent glory, Hee conſumed their ſhort daies in vanity, and no more was ſpoken of them but that they had flouriſhed. As <hi>Iob</hi> cals them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yeſterdaies men, who like to <hi>Solſtitinlis
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13672:56"/>herba,</hi> ſuddenly ſprung vp, and ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decayed. When <hi>Nabuchadonoſor</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braued God, he was depoſed from his throne, he fed on graſſe, and the dew of heauen wet him like graſſe, to make him know by ſenſible experience what inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude he would not vnderſtand. <hi>Lord what is man that thou regardeſt him,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid?</hi> the poore ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> or the rich Sonne of Man. <hi>Man that is borne of woman hath no long time to liue, he commeth forth like a flower, and is cut downe:</hi> Take him in his beauty, what is beauty? but a brag of nature, an illuſion of deſire, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haling into vanity: a ſelfe adoring idoll, the firſt baite of ſin, which breathing vpon the concupiſcentiall eye of the woman, hath euer ſince with her, and by her, continued the concubine of a doting ſoule. This felicity of body (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) what is it, but <hi>vrbana veſtis,</hi> a trimme ſuit vpon the ſoule which inuites the Thiefe and Murderer, and is often extreme dangerous to them that weare it: Witneſſe the examples of <hi>Sara</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whoſe wanton Miſtreſſe would haue ſtript him alſo of his chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But in the luſtre of thoſe colours,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13672:56"/>if the white of ſimplicity, and the red of modeſty bee away, it may take the vulgar, but the wiſe eſteeme it no other then a gariſh garment on the backe of fooles. Come on therefore, let vs enioy the good things that are preſent, and let no flower of the ſpring paſſe by vs. Let vs crowne our ſelues with Roſe-buds before they bee withered: let vs take our part of iollitie, and leaue the ſignes of voluptuouſneſſe in all places. Thus talke theſe wantons, when they inuite their fellowes to repentance: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeaſonable follies are more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, but when age reuokes theſe fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue pleaſures, renewing youth with artificiall deuices, as if they were aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that ſeaſon which brings them neerer vnto God, &amp; deliuers them from the vnquiet perturbations of the fleſh, What argues it but that they are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to make the vtmoſt farthing of the good of this life, and will forgoe no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light heere for hope of recompence in the life to come. A painted flower in Summer who reſpects when they are produced by nature? and in Winter which hath other fruitions, it is vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13672:57"/>and againſt Nature. Now well doth the Apoſtle heere call this, and whatſoeuer is amiable, the flowre of graſſe, or the flower of the field. For after that <hi>Adam</hi> was tranſlated out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, all his glory was but wild and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: as beſt appeareth in the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vaſt Regions of the earth, where <hi>verus cultus</hi> the true worſhip is wanting, where euery flower of beauty is the prey of violent, and vnruled luſt. And yet theſe ſmall parcels of ciuill States which are ſo fenced with Lawes and Religion, where beauty is manured by education, nouriſhed by ſpeciall care, and cheriſhed by beſt counſell, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>Quem mulcent aurae, firmat ſol, educat imber:</hi> Yet how ſeldome is it preſerued and kept ſafe, that the inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of forraine luſt do not breake in and deflowre it? But let theſe flowers fade, the glory of wealth will not leaue vs. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> anſwereth, As the flower of the graſſe, the rich paſſe away. For the Sun is no ſooner riſen with a burning heate, but it withereth the graſſe, and the flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the faſhion of it periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13672:57"/>So alſo ſhall the rich man fade away in his waies. Name mee any other excellence, and yee ſhall find it but a choice flower of ſhort continuance. Wit, and eloquence are but bloſſomes, which falling off, the fruit of wiſedome ſucceedeth and vnderſtanding. To conclude, whatſoeuer is deſireable in the world, whatſoeuer fawnes vpon the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of men, whatſoeuer makes our wils idolatrous: all is but a flower of graſſe, a thing of ſmall vſe, but no fruition. Yea the Diuine Maieſty hath ſo abbreuiated all earthly glory, that thoſe excellencies which ſpring from an immortall roote, and are by nature not lyable to vanity and conſumption, yet they will not thriue vpon earth: and though they bee illuſtrious for a time they are ſuddenly ſnatcht from vs. Piety, and goodneſſe, and Diuine knowledge, which perfume the ſinfull world, and ſend vp a ſweet ſauour of pacification into heauen, how thinnely do they grow, and how quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they exhaled? <hi>Saluete flores mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum, quos lucis ipſo in limine, Chriſti inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor ſuſtulit, ceu turbo naſcentes roſas, flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res martyrum:</hi> Innocent martyrs, whoſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13672:58"/>names Chriſt hath written red in letters: of bloud in earth, and of gold in heauen. The Flower of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: whether you will call him a Starre, or a Flower, the skill of neither languague can determine: and the Holy Ghoſt (I thinke) left it ambiguous, to ſignifie that Hee is the Off-ſpring of both, both heauen and earth. As flowers are ſtarres on earth, and ſtarres are heauenly flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers. This coeleſtiall Flower was no ſooner ſprung, and declared by a Starre, but the rude hand was ready to nip him off: and Hee had not long adorned the earth with His glorious preſence, but in the latitude of his goodlieſt yeares, Hee breathed out his ſweete Soule, And who can expreſſe the abrupt cruelty of His bitter ending? he bowed downe his Head: It is a circumſtance which none but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Diſciple of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome obſerueth:
<q>
                  <l>— In<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> humeros ceruìxcollapſa recumbit,</l>
                  <l>Purpureus veluti cum flos ſucciſus aratro</l>
                  <l>Langueſcit moriens, laſſoue papauera collo</l>
                  <l>Demiſere eaput. —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:13672:58"/>
By this geſture hee might ſignifie that his triumphant Soule was now deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to the loweſt parts of the earth: Whence, according to the deepe roote of his humiliation, hee roſe againe, and aſcended aboue the higheſt heauens, and we with him: For heeres our comfort, that being complanted in the ſimilitude of his death, wee ſhall bee made partakers of his reſurrection. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe,</hi> there is mortality and depreſſion, all fleſh ſhall ſee the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, there is the ſpring and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. This is the true condition of our nature: Although death reape a whole field, &amp; leaue no flower, nothing that is greene, yet the roote remaining, all fleſh ſhall bee reſtored, all glory ſhall be new coloured: Yea and with aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: <hi>Lucrodamno,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> with lucre-loſſe, with honeſt vſury. It heere growes in weakeneſſe, it ſhall there riſe in ſtrength; it is cut downe in diſhonor, it ſprings in honour: here naturall, there ſpirituall. It is a Plant whoſe flower ſhal bee exaſperate with no thorny care, not greenneſſe be euerwithered. What hurt, what hurt then can death doe vs? wee
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13672:59"/>ſhall not laugh heere: Nor ſhall wee weepe. We ſhall not bee admired, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall wee bee contemned: But wee ſhall do no more good, but the good we haue done ſhall follow vs: But we ſhall not liue to lament ſinne, but the ſinnes wee haue lamented ſhall bee forgiuen vs. Laſtly, as the day ſprings after night, and the Sunne reuiues, and flowers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and the earth is refreſhed: <hi>Sic nos reſurgere deuota mente credimus,</hi> So wee beleeue to liue againe: Which that wee may do with him, he grant which liueth and raigneth, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the fourth Sermon.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13672:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
